<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Irena, a tragedy</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45772</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11849802</idno>
  <idno type="VID">49923</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240860539</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16046</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11849802</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 498:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Irena, a tragedy</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert White for Octavian Pulleyn junior ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49923:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49923:1"/>
            <p>IRENA, A TRAGEDY.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>LICENSED,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>October</hi> 13. 1664.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Roger L'Estrange.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert White</hi> for <hi>Octavian Pulleyn</hi> Junior, at the sign of the Bible in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard near the little North-door. 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:49923:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49923:2"/>
            <head>Drammatis Personae.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>MAhomet</hi> the Second, surnam'd the Great, Emperour of the Turks.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Carazias, Mahomet's</hi> Lievtenant General in Europe:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mustapha</hi> Bassa, who had bin educated and brought up with <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Zoganus, Caly</hi> Bassa, <hi>Mahometes,</hi> three other Bassa's.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Aga</hi> of the Ianizaries.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Osman,</hi> and <hi>Murat,</hi> two Ianizaries.</item>
               <item>An Eunuch</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:49923:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Justinianus,</hi> Generall to the late Greek Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Constantinus Palaeologus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Honorius,</hi> Friend to <hi>Justinianus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Irena,</hi> and <hi>Perinthia,</hi> Two Ladies.</item>
               <item>Guards and Attendants.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Scene, <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:49923:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49923:4"/>
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF by your faces I can guess; to day,</l>
               <l>I fear but ill success attends our Play.</l>
               <l>Your looks me-thinks to me seems so severe,</l>
               <l>As if that none but Criticks now were here.</l>
               <l>And we've small hopes our Play should take; There sits</l>
               <l>So many here, that are, or would be, Wits.</l>
               <l>Y're lately grown so critically wise,</l>
               <l>There's scarce a Play that's writ, but you despise.</l>
               <l>And to speak truth, Nothing almost can be</l>
               <l>From your dislik, or from your censure, free.</l>
               <l>Such Fate our Authour fears; I heard him guess,</l>
               <l>And swear his Play would have the like success;</l>
               <l>But yet he say's, He cares not; for he writ</l>
               <l>Not to gain praise, or to be call'd a wit:</l>
               <l>The motives which induc'd him for to write</l>
               <l>This Play, he say's, was most for your delight.</l>
               <l>He hopes for that, if for no other cause,</l>
               <l>(Though undeserv'd) you'll give him your Applause.</l>
               <l>And hopes you'll pardon all the faults you find,</l>
               <l>Since that to recreate you 'twas design'd.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49923:4"/>
            <head>IRENA, A Tragedie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. I. SCEN. I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Osman, <hi>and</hi> Murat, <hi>two Janizaries.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>HA! my eyes deceive me, or that should be</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Murat</hi> my old Companion; 'tis he, I'le to him.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Murat,</hi> 'tis long since last I saw your face,</l>
                     <l>You're now most welcome to your friends embrace.</l>
                     <l>How is't old Comerade, methinks th'art thriven,</l>
                     <l>And art grown fat by the Wars, What news I pray</l>
                     <l>From th' Army?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Murat.</speaker>
                     <l>Why little, And that I suppose you are</l>
                     <l>Not ignorant of, For th'art of the Emperours</l>
                     <l>Guards (as I take it), And you Courtiers seldom</l>
                     <l>Want Intelligence.</l>
                     <l>To relate to you what Battles we have fought,</l>
                     <l>What Towns, and Castles we have taken, and</l>
                     <l>What valliant actions our Great Bassa</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carazias</hi> (under whose command I was)</l>
                     <l>Perform'd against our Enemies, were but</l>
                     <l>To tell you what you know already.</l>
                     <l>But may not I take liberty, and make</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49923:5"/>
                     <l>The same demand to you, and ask what news</l>
                     <l>At Court, What Enterprise is next providing</l>
                     <l>For us? Whither we shall have Wars with <hi>Persia,</hi> or no,</l>
                     <l>Or with some other Prince? Or what Beauty</l>
                     <l>In all the Seraglio is now so happy,</l>
                     <l>As to please our Glorious Sultan?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>Our news at Court is such I shame to tell it,</l>
                     <l>Nor indeed durst I, but that 'tis now grown</l>
                     <l>Common, And not the Great-ones only, but</l>
                     <l>The Mean-ones too take liberty to talk</l>
                     <l>Their pleasure; And though it be discretion</l>
                     <l>In us Courtiers, to be both deaf, and blind,</l>
                     <l>Neither to hear, nor see our Prince's faults,</l>
                     <l>Much less discover 'em; But if we do,</l>
                     <l>Rather to praise 'em as Vertues, then to</l>
                     <l>Disparage 'em as Vices; yet all men</l>
                     <l>So dislike our Sultans present actions,</l>
                     <l>That none that are true friends, and that desire</l>
                     <l>Increase, and Prosperity to our Empire,</l>
                     <l>Can hold their peace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Murat.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou strik'st me with amazement <hi>Osman,</hi> Nor</l>
                     <l>Can I believe, but that all the actions</l>
                     <l>Of our Sultan tends to the glory of</l>
                     <l>His Empire; but thou know'st I have been absent</l>
                     <l>This twelve-month from the Court, and been in places</l>
                     <l>Where (by reason of their distance) we could</l>
                     <l>Have but small Intelligence. Our Bassa</l>
                     <l>Being commanded to go and carry</l>
                     <l>War into the Enemies Country, lest they</l>
                     <l>Should have assisted the Grecian Emperour,</l>
                     <l>And so diverted, or hindred the intended</l>
                     <l>Enterprize, of our Great Emperour</l>
                     <l>On this Imperial City.</l>
                     <l>Therefore, good <hi>Osman,</hi> Pray, do you relate</l>
                     <l>What wonder's this concerns our Empire's fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you desire it, I will—</l>
                     <l>I think I shall not need to rehearse to</l>
                     <l>You all those remarkable accidents</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49923:5"/>
                     <l>Which happen'd during the siege of this great</l>
                     <l>City of <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What assaults we gave to the besieged,</l>
                     <l>With how much valour perform'd on our part,</l>
                     <l>And with how much obstinacy, and resistance</l>
                     <l>On theirs, and how that at last (after a</l>
                     <l>Long, and tedious siege) we won the Town by</l>
                     <l>An assault, And that which facilitated</l>
                     <l>Our conquest (as afterwards we understood)</l>
                     <l>Was, that <hi>Justinianus</hi> the Emperours</l>
                     <l>Valiant General, having receiv'd some</l>
                     <l>Wounds (in the defence of a breach we had</l>
                     <l>Made i'the wall) through effusion of</l>
                     <l>Blood was forc'd to retire; which much</l>
                     <l>Discouraged his men who (believing 'em</l>
                     <l>Mortal, as indeed they were, for his body</l>
                     <l>Was afterwards found amongst the dead)</l>
                     <l>Immediately fled, and by their flight</l>
                     <l>Left us not only possest of the Breach,</l>
                     <l>But of the City too.</l>
                     <l>And that the Emperour <hi>Constantinus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Palaeologus</hi> himself striving to escape</l>
                     <l>Amongst the rest was trod to death.</l>
                     <l>These things I say I need not insist upon</l>
                     <l>They being sufficiently known. Fame</l>
                     <l>Having related'em to all the world,</l>
                     <l>Nor do I think you ignorant of 'em.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Murat.</speaker>
                     <l>No <hi>Osman,</hi> all this I know, having heard</l>
                     <l>The same related by some persons that</l>
                     <l>Resorted from your Army, to our Camp.</l>
                     <l>But pray go on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>The City thus being taken, our men</l>
                     <l>Had the plunder granted 'em as a reward</l>
                     <l>For all those miseries they had indur'd</l>
                     <l>Before it.</l>
                     <l>One Souldier more ventrous then the rest entring boldly</l>
                     <l>Into a stately Palace (wherewith this</l>
                     <l>City abounds) found it by all deserted</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49923:6"/>
                     <l>Only (as afterwards himself related)</l>
                     <l>In an upper room he found some women.</l>
                     <l>And amongst the rest one extreamly fair,</l>
                     <l>And who by the costliness of her habit,</l>
                     <l>And the respect the others pay'd her, seem'd</l>
                     <l>To be their Mistriss, who immediately</l>
                     <l>Upon the Souldiers approach (apprehending</l>
                     <l>Some violence) fell into a swound.</l>
                     <l>The Souldier (not caring for the others)</l>
                     <l>Seiz'd on her as this Prisoner, and as</l>
                     <l>A prey beyond his expectation.</l>
                     <l>And carrying her to his Quarters, there</l>
                     <l>Recover'd her.</l>
                     <l>But finding her to be so fair a Creature</l>
                     <l>And far unfit to yield to his unruly,</l>
                     <l>And brutish appetite (incourag'd through</l>
                     <l>Hope of a great reward) presented her</l>
                     <l>To the Sultan: who at first, although</l>
                     <l>He was taken with her form, seem'd not much</l>
                     <l>To mind her, He being then imploy'd</l>
                     <l>About giving orders for the securing</l>
                     <l>Of the City; but committed her to</l>
                     <l>The charge of one of his chief Eunuchs.</l>
                     <l>But scarce had a month expir'd, and he</l>
                     <l>Taken some order, towards the settling,</l>
                     <l>And establishing in peace, and quietness</l>
                     <l>His new conquered Empire:</l>
                     <l>But he bethought himself of Beautious</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi> (for so she's call'd) who's fair Image</l>
                     <l>Soly possest his thoughts, and having sent</l>
                     <l>For her to his presence, found her not only</l>
                     <l>To exceed those past <hi>Idaea's</hi> he had</l>
                     <l>Taken of her, when she was orecome</l>
                     <l>With fear, and grief, but even Imagination</l>
                     <l>Its self. And although she wore a sorrow</l>
                     <l>On her face that well exprest the trouble</l>
                     <l>Of her mind;</l>
                     <l>Yet like as glorious <hi>Phoebus,</hi> when a mist</l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49923:6"/>
                     <l>Oreclouds his beautious, and resplendent face,</l>
                     <l>His golden rayes, and beams does then appear,</l>
                     <l>Less bright, than in a Skie serene and clear.</l>
                     <l>So her fair eyes, and face, though now o'recast</l>
                     <l>With clouds of fear, and grief, yet those once past,</l>
                     <l>Her pristine beauty gain'd again might she,</l>
                     <l>Ador'd be for the Sea-born Deity,</l>
                     <l>And might contend for Beauties Empire then,</l>
                     <l>With that fair Queen, ador'd by Gods, and Men.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> at this second interview</l>
                     <l>Seem'd far more amaz'd, than at the first,</l>
                     <l>Admiring to see so many excellencies,</l>
                     <l>And perfections meet together in this</l>
                     <l>Fair creature, believing her rather to be</l>
                     <l>Some coelestial Apparition,</l>
                     <l>Than a terrestial Creature.</l>
                     <l>For certainly Nature ne're form'd a piece</l>
                     <l>More divinely rare. Having had his eyes</l>
                     <l>Fixt a long time on her fair visage,</l>
                     <l>He at last broke silence to this effect.</l>
                     <l>Madam (said he) pardon the rudeness of</l>
                     <l>A Prince, who being wholly taken up</l>
                     <l>With admiration of your divine</l>
                     <l>Perfections, has so far forgot himself,</l>
                     <l>As to continue so long silent, and</l>
                     <l>Without rendring to you those honours that</l>
                     <l>Are due to so Excellent a Person</l>
                     <l>She reply'd, That she was altogether</l>
                     <l>Unworthy to receive such favours</l>
                     <l>From so great a Prince, and that since by her</l>
                     <l>Cruel Fate, and the chance of War, she was</l>
                     <l>Now become his slave, she was not so far</l>
                     <l>Ignorant of what either belong'd to</l>
                     <l>Her present condition, or misfortune,</l>
                     <l>But that she knew, how ill it did agree</l>
                     <l>With her present state, to admit of such</l>
                     <l>Complements from so great a Monarch.</l>
                     <l>And so after some other discourse had</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49923:7"/>
                     <l>Past between 'em, the Emperour caus'd her</l>
                     <l>To be conducted to one of the most</l>
                     <l>Stately appartments in all the Palace.</l>
                     <l>And gave strict command that she should be</l>
                     <l>Respected as his <hi>Sultaness,</hi> not his slave.</l>
                     <l>Since that time, he has made addresses of</l>
                     <l>Affection to her, but, as they say (who</l>
                     <l>Have leave to come near e'm) she continues</l>
                     <l>Yet chast, and will not so much as indure</l>
                     <l>To hear of any thing that tends to her</l>
                     <l>Dishonour; And that which is most strange,</l>
                     <l>Is the power she has o're the <hi>Sultan.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For by her beauty she does so charm up</l>
                     <l>All his Passions, that he dares not so much</l>
                     <l>As once think of attempting that by violence,</l>
                     <l>Which he cannot obtain by fair means, and Submission.</l>
                     <l>Nay Love, that Tyrannical, and Imperious</l>
                     <l>Passion, so predominates, and tyrannizeth</l>
                     <l>O're his Reason, that he now seems to have</l>
                     <l>Buried in oblivion all his former</l>
                     <l>Desires of Empire, and of Glory;</l>
                     <l>And seems now to fix his thoughts on nothing,</l>
                     <l>But on the fair <hi>Irena</hi>'s Image.</l>
                     <l>All those former designs of War, and conquering</l>
                     <l>Empires, are now laid by; his chief design</l>
                     <l>Is now to please his Mistress.</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers, once the only objects of his</l>
                     <l>Delight, are now grown, the objects of his Scorn.</l>
                     <l>And that Army once for discipline, and</l>
                     <l>Valour, the terrour, and admiration</l>
                     <l>Of the whole world, is now by Licentiousness,</l>
                     <l>And Liberty, Ease, and Rest, grown the scorn,</l>
                     <l>And derision of all Nations.</l>
                     <l>Nor is it easie to represent to you</l>
                     <l>How much the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s present humour is</l>
                     <l>Resented and dislik'd of, not only</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49923:7"/>
                     <l>By the Bassa's, and other Superiour</l>
                     <l>Officers, but also by the Janizaries,</l>
                     <l>And other inferiour Souldiers too.</l>
                     <l>So that unless it please Heaven to cause</l>
                     <l>Some sudden alteration in our</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan</hi>'s humour, 'tis to be fear'd they will</l>
                     <l>Break out into some rash, and sudden tumult.</l>
                     <l>And perhaps in their rage, and fury, act</l>
                     <l>Those things that they will afterwards themselves</l>
                     <l>Repent of. For they talk high already, and</l>
                     <l>Begin publickly to report that he</l>
                     <l>Is unworthy to govern 'em, and that</l>
                     <l>It would be well done to deprive him of</l>
                     <l>The Government, and to bestow on Prince</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bajazet</hi> his Son, both his Empire, and His Throne.</l>
                     <l>And 'tis to be more than fear'd, that these black</l>
                     <l>Clouds of discontent, are but the dismal</l>
                     <l>Portents of an ensuing storm.</l>
                     <l>And his condition is so much the more</l>
                     <l>Deplorable, since that he is not able</l>
                     <l>To discern his own danger; for Love so</l>
                     <l>Blinds his reason, that he cannot perceive</l>
                     <l>It himself. And there's none that dare be so bold,</l>
                     <l>And ventrous, as to declare it to him.</l>
                     <l>For whose 'ere should go about to attempt</l>
                     <l>It, would draw an inevitable ruine</l>
                     <l>On himself.</l>
                     <l>This, <hi>Murat,</hi> is our present wretched condition,</l>
                     <l>And if it please not Heaven speedily</l>
                     <l>To divert that threatning storm, that now hangs</l>
                     <l>O're our heads, we are like to be most miserable,</l>
                     <l>And act that against our selves, which the</l>
                     <l>United power of our Enemies could never do.</l>
                     <l>Thus then you see how Love conspires with fate,</l>
                     <l>Both for to ruine, and destroy our state.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Murat.</speaker>
                     <l>I must confess, <hi>Osman,</hi> you story is</l>
                     <l>Strange, and full of wonder. For who could e're</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49923:8"/>
                     <l>Believe so strange an alteration</l>
                     <l>In our <hi>Sultan</hi>'s warlike humour;</l>
                     <l>And that Love should e're find room in a breast</l>
                     <l>Like his, that was prepossest so much before</l>
                     <l>With ambition, and desire of glory.</l>
                     <l>But by this we may see, That Princes too,</l>
                     <l>As well as persons of a lower rank,</l>
                     <l>Are subject to that Tyrannical Passion.</l>
                     <l>Nor can all the Divinity that we</l>
                     <l>Attribute to 'em, defend 'em from those</l>
                     <l>Frailties, which we by the weakness of our</l>
                     <l>Nature are subject to.</l>
                     <l>And though they are all other Pow'rs above,</l>
                     <l>Yet they are subject to the Pow'r of Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a fatal truth that we now find</l>
                     <l>Confirm'd by sad experience; else who</l>
                     <l>Would have believ'ed that our glorious <hi>Sultan,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>On whose frown, or smile depended the fate</l>
                     <l>Of Nations, should thus tamely have yielded.</l>
                     <l>Up his Liberty to a Womans eyes.</l>
                     <l>Or that his generous soul could ever have</l>
                     <l>Been thus subjected, and made Beauties slave.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Murat</hi> let's go, the Bassa's appear,</l>
                     <l>This is no place for us, whilst they are here.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. I. SCEN. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Carazias, Caly Bassa, Mustapha, Zoganus, Mahometes <hi>and the</hi> Aga <hi>of the Janezaries.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>THe news you tell me seems to me so strange,</l>
                     <l>That, Generous Friends, I ask your pardon, if</l>
                     <l>That as yet I want Faith to credit it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly Bassa.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, 'tis so strange to us, that had we not</l>
                     <l>Been present, and been eye-witnesses of our</l>
                     <l>Emperours weakness, we might have had</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49923:8"/>
                     <l>Just cause to suspect, that it had been some</l>
                     <l>Inchantment to delude our senses.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahometes.</speaker>
                     <l>But now it is so evident made out,</l>
                     <l>That there's no room at all more left for doubt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zogan.</speaker>
                     <l>How I could curse those Destinies, and Powers</l>
                     <l>That rule our Empires fate, When I consider</l>
                     <l>How they suffer a Womans beauty thus</l>
                     <l>To Ecclipse all our former glory.</l>
                     <l>For what a shame and dishonour 'tis to</l>
                     <l>All our former glorious actions to see</l>
                     <l>How those conquering Ensigns, which when display'd</l>
                     <l>Hurl'd terrour on the world, are now fur'ld up</l>
                     <l>And lay'd as Trophees at a Womans feet.</l>
                     <l>What pitty 'tis, those Banners that did brave</l>
                     <l>The world, should pay such homage to a slave!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay sure no mortal Beauty could ere have power</l>
                     <l>Thus to bewitch our <hi>Sultan</hi>'s senses,</l>
                     <l>I rather believe 'tis some Infernal</l>
                     <l>Spirit, conjur'd up (by our Enemies)</l>
                     <l>From Hells Lowest Regions, to take</l>
                     <l>This pleasing form, and shape upon 'um, thus</l>
                     <l>To delude our <hi>Sultan.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But since that he continues in such a</l>
                     <l>Lethargy, And that 'tis Equally</l>
                     <l>Impossible for us, or sense</l>
                     <l>Of honour, to awake him,</l>
                     <l>'Tis fit (since that the safety of the State</l>
                     <l>Requires it) we should have recourse to other</l>
                     <l>Means then those we have try'd already.</l>
                     <l>Nor do I fear to say, that 'tis dishonourable</l>
                     <l>For us to be govern'd by a Prince, that</l>
                     <l>Cannot govern himself.</l>
                     <l>For how can he with Justice punish those</l>
                     <l>Crimes in us, which he is guilty of himself.</l>
                     <l>Let's then magnanimously go with one</l>
                     <l>Accord, and assault the Palace, and there</l>
                     <l>By force pull this fair Slave from out his arms,</l>
                     <l>And offer her up a victim to our</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49923:9"/>
                     <l>Neglected honour.</l>
                     <l>That done, Ler's deprive him of the goverment,</l>
                     <l>And bestow the Empire on Prince <hi>Bajazet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His Son. For after such actions perform'd</l>
                     <l>As these we must ne're expect the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s</l>
                     <l>Pardon. The Prince will be easily induc'd</l>
                     <l>To pardon us, when he considers that</l>
                     <l>T'was we that plac'd him in the throne.</l>
                     <l>But if he should deny it, Have not we</l>
                     <l>Arms in our hands, to make our owns conditions.</l>
                     <l>Nor is what I propound hard to be effected;</l>
                     <l>For we shall find resistance from none,</l>
                     <l>Except from some Persons whom the Emperours</l>
                     <l>Presence may make valiant.</l>
                     <l>The Janizaries, and Souldiers are already</l>
                     <l>Highly incens'd. And the People (weary</l>
                     <l>Of his government) desire nothing</l>
                     <l>More than change.</l>
                     <l>Why then, Let us our several int'rests joyn,</l>
                     <l>Our's and the States, Let's all in one combine.</l>
                     <l>The State can't suffer more than it indures,</l>
                     <l>Desp'rate diseases must have desp'rate cures.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zoga.</speaker>
                     <l>Generous <hi>Aga,</hi> Your counsail I approve</l>
                     <l>As truly noble, and such as the present</l>
                     <l>Necessity of affairs require.</l>
                     <l>And I dare ingage that there are none here</l>
                     <l>Of such degenerate spirits, but that does</l>
                     <l>Esteem, and approve it to be</l>
                     <l>Worthy a Person, whom that no respect,</l>
                     <l>Can cause his Countries safety to neglect.</l>
                     <l>And for my self I am resolv'd to aid</l>
                     <l>You, both with my Life, and fortune.</l>
                     <l>And I will cause, disasters to prevent,</l>
                     <l>The Euxine troops to second your intent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>And I to yours, the Asian troops will joyn,</l>
                     <l>To shew that your consent agrees with mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly Bassa.</speaker>
                     <l>And I'le be ready; but appoint the hour,</l>
                     <l>To serve you with my Interest, and pow'r.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49923:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Since that the Empires safety lyes at stake,</l>
                     <l>I'le boldly follow in th'assault you make.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Then let's strait go, each to those several</l>
                     <l>Troops committed to our charge, and prepare 'em</l>
                     <l>This night t'assault the Palace.</l>
                     <l>Come let's away, and make all sure,</l>
                     <l>The Janizaries I'le secure.</l>
                     <l>Great actions seldome but are crost,</l>
                     <l>And by delay are alwayes lost.</l>
                     <l>Come Generous Friends, Come let's away—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay first, and hear what I can say—</l>
                     <l>What fury, nay what madness, Brave Companions,</l>
                     <l>Does now possess your brains? Do you consider</l>
                     <l>What you go about, or against whom you</l>
                     <l>Take up arms? Will you then turn Rebels to</l>
                     <l>That Prince, to whom you owe both your Lives and</l>
                     <l>Fortunes; And through whose fortune, and conduct</l>
                     <l>You have Victorious been in two and</l>
                     <l>Thirty Battails. And although I cannot</l>
                     <l>Excuse, or at least defend, his late</l>
                     <l>Effeminate actions, yet consider</l>
                     <l>That 'tis an excess of Love, and that that</l>
                     <l>Passion ever predominates, and usurps</l>
                     <l>It's power most, over noble and</l>
                     <l>Generous souls.</l>
                     <l>Besides he is our Emperour to whom</l>
                     <l>We have all sworn allegiance.</l>
                     <l>And, Pray let's take heed lest (by breaking of</l>
                     <l>Our oaths) we draw down heavens vengeance on</l>
                     <l>Our heads. For certainly if heaven punishes</l>
                     <l>Those perjuries, we commit towards common</l>
                     <l>And Inferiour Persons; Much more it will</l>
                     <l>Revenge, those we commit towards Princes.</l>
                     <l>Consider too, what a shame and reproach</l>
                     <l>It will be to all our former glory,</l>
                     <l>If that now at Last, after having conquer'd</l>
                     <l>Twelve Kingdoms, and two Empires, we should make</l>
                     <l>Use of our victorious Arms to dispossess</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49923:10"/>
                     <l>Our natural Prince of's Throne.</l>
                     <l>No, Generous Friends, Let's ne're leave such a stain</l>
                     <l>Upon our memories; Let's rather try</l>
                     <l>To perswade him to conquer his foolish</l>
                     <l>Passion, And to leave this fair Greek, And again</l>
                     <l>To lead us forth against our Enemies,</l>
                     <l>To obtain new Victories, and Triumphs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zoga.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mustapha,</hi> I think it something strange</l>
                     <l>This counsail should proceed from you, who are</l>
                     <l>So well acquainted with his fierce, and cruell</l>
                     <l>Nature, And how Implacable he is</l>
                     <l>To forgive those that offend him: For who</l>
                     <l>Think you amongst us, is so weary of</l>
                     <l>His own Life, As that he dares to declare</l>
                     <l>To him, that which you propound?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>If that be all, since the Empires safety</l>
                     <l>Does require it, I dare do it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>If you have a mind to give the Mutes</l>
                     <l>Imployment, you may.</l>
                     <l>But if you valew so little your own</l>
                     <l>Life, yet give us leave to set a higher</l>
                     <l>Price on ours, than to be rul'd by your</l>
                     <l>Foolish counsail.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>No <hi>Mustapha,</hi> ne're think with your dull Rhetorick</l>
                     <l>To make us alter what we have decreed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly Bassa.</speaker>
                     <l>You may as soon force Nature to uncreate</l>
                     <l>The world, And turn it into Chaos, as</l>
                     <l>To divert us from our fixt resolution.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Methinks 'tis strange that Loyalty should find</l>
                     <l>No more a lodging in your breasts, sure she</l>
                     <l>Has left the Earth, and with <hi>Astraea</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is fled to heaven. Consider how in</l>
                     <l>Nature 'tis preposterous for the members</l>
                     <l>To conspire against the head, which if it</l>
                     <l>But miscarries all the rest must perish—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Curse on this Dull Philosophie—</l>
                     <l>Come let's away, the State requires our swords,</l>
                     <l>Let's spend the time in action, not in words.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes praeter Mustapha.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49923:10"/>
                  <head>Actus I. Scena III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Mustapha</hi> solus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>What strange Fate attends on Princes actions?</l>
                     <l>Who would have thought this <hi>Sultan,</hi> lately ador'd</l>
                     <l>By these Perfidious Bassa's as if he</l>
                     <l>Had been some Deity, (and to whom they</l>
                     <l>Are beholding for all their present greatness)</l>
                     <l>Should so by one weak action, make 'em lose</l>
                     <l>The good opinion they had of him,</l>
                     <l>As that they now dare take up arms against him!</l>
                     <l>How miserable are those Princes, that</l>
                     <l>When they commit faults can find none that dares</l>
                     <l>Be so Loyall as to declare it to 'em</l>
                     <l>This their treacherous design, an if not</l>
                     <l>Speedily prevented, will be the Emperours Ruine.</l>
                     <l>And since none dares be so bold, and faithfull,</l>
                     <l>As to declare to him his weakness, and</l>
                     <l>The danger he is in, I'le do it</l>
                     <l>My self.</l>
                     <l>The familiarity that has formerly</l>
                     <l>Been between us, as being educated,</l>
                     <l>And brought up together, and the favour</l>
                     <l>Wherewith he has since been pleas'd to honour</l>
                     <l>Me, makes me hope to be succesfull.</l>
                     <l>And though I know his nature (when crost) to</l>
                     <l>Be stern, and cruell, yet if I should miscarry</l>
                     <l>I shall have this honour entail'd upon</l>
                     <l>My memory, That I dyed a Sacrifice</l>
                     <l>To my Prince, and Countreys safety.</l>
                     <l>For, should I not declare it to him,</l>
                     <l>I might justly be supected to have</l>
                     <l>Had a hand in their design.</l>
                     <l>"For he that knows of Treason, and conceals it,</l>
                     <l>"Is as much a Traytor as he that acts it.</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49923:11"/>
                     <l>"No, I resolve that I will that reveal,</l>
                     <l>"Which would be treachery for to conceal;</l>
                     <l>"And what Perfidious men these Bassa's are</l>
                     <l>"I'le straitwayes to the Emperour declare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus I. Scena IV.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet, <hi>and an</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Have you been with the fair <hi>Irena,</hi> and</l>
                     <l>Deliver'd to her the message I commanded?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Majesties commands I have obey'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>And how did she receive the fair Present</l>
                     <l>That I sent her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>She seem'd much pleas'd, and with an air mixt both</l>
                     <l>With modesty and sweetness commanded</l>
                     <l>Me to render your Majesty humble</l>
                     <l>Thanks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis well, withdraw —</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Eun.</stage>
                     <l>I cannot but admire at my strange fate,</l>
                     <l>When I consider how that now of late</l>
                     <l>I am become Love's Votary, and must be</l>
                     <l>Contented with that foolish Boy's decree.</l>
                     <l>For is't not strange, that I whose power does awe</l>
                     <l>The world, should thus from Love receive a Law?</l>
                     <l>For who'd have thought, that e're a heart like mine,</l>
                     <l>It's Liberty to Beauty should resign?</l>
                     <l>Or that my haughty courage ere should have</l>
                     <l>Pay'd such submission to a Beauteous slave?</l>
                     <l>But yet Alas, when I my heart a prize</l>
                     <l>Yielded to fair <hi>Irena</hi>'s beauteous Eyes,</l>
                     <l>I did become her slave, and straitwayes wore</l>
                     <l>Those chains, and fetters, she did wear before.</l>
                     <l>Yet I Esteem't more glorious for to be</l>
                     <l>Her slave, than to possess my Monarchie.</l>
                     <l>For what avails it me that I possess</l>
                     <l>So vast an Empire, for can that makes less</l>
                     <l>The sense of my misfortunes; since no part</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49923:11"/>
                     <l>That I can claim in fair <hi>Irena</hi>'s heart.</l>
                     <l>And since the fair <hi>Irena</hi> proves unkind,</l>
                     <l>Can that give ease to my afflicted mind?</l>
                     <l>No, I with all my Greatness ne're could move</l>
                     <l>Either, as yet, her Pity, or her Love.</l>
                     <l>Nor dare I venture that by force to take,</l>
                     <l>Which to surrender yet I cannot make.</l>
                     <l>For strait those radiant beams shot from her Eyes</l>
                     <l>Makes me to quit my bold design, and tyes</l>
                     <l>Up all my Passions; And strait she unarms</l>
                     <l>Me of my fury, by her powerfull charms.</l>
                     <l>But yet I'le try if from her I can gain,</l>
                     <l>Ought that may ease, or mitigate my pain.</l>
                     <l>To which if she consent, then she shall be</l>
                     <l>Both Mistris of my Empire, and of Me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. II. SCEN. I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Justinianus <hi>solus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>WHen I consider to what various</l>
                     <l>Accidents, and disasters mans Life is</l>
                     <l>Subject to, I cannot but admire what</l>
                     <l>Strange Vicissitudes there are in fate.</l>
                     <l>And wonder more how they are brought about,</l>
                     <l>The less I can their hidden cause find out.</l>
                     <l>For who'd have thought, That I, a Person</l>
                     <l>Lately so happy, that I thought my self</l>
                     <l>Above the reach of Fortune, And durst have</l>
                     <l>Defied the malice of that Inconstant</l>
                     <l>Goddess, Thinking it beyond her power</l>
                     <l>To make me miserable; Find my self</l>
                     <l>Now so wretched, that 'tis my greatest</l>
                     <l>Torment to think I have been happy.</l>
                     <l>Lately I was possest of all I could</l>
                     <l>Desire, High in my Prince's favour,</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49923:12"/>
                     <l>Belov'd of by the People:</l>
                     <l>But that, which I esteem'd above the rest,</l>
                     <l>I held a place in fair <hi>Irena</hi>'s brest.</l>
                     <l>For I with Justice there could claim a part,</l>
                     <l>Since I had then some int'rest in her heart.</l>
                     <l>But now at once I am depriv'd of all</l>
                     <l>my past felicity.</l>
                     <l>My Prince slain by those Barbarians that</l>
                     <l>Now possess the Empire, The people enslaved,</l>
                     <l>And (that which grieves me most) the fair <hi>Irena</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is become the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Mistris, And though</l>
                     <l>I have been curious to make inquiry</l>
                     <l>How he uses her, And cannot hear but</l>
                     <l>That, as yet, he treats her nobly, with that</l>
                     <l>Respect, which both her birth, and beauty claims:</l>
                     <l>Yet I have reason to suspect that 'tis</l>
                     <l>Not his Generosity, but his Lust</l>
                     <l>Exacts this treatment from him.</l>
                     <l>And though it were Impious to mistrust</l>
                     <l>Her vertue, yet who knows whether this</l>
                     <l>Barbarian, when he has vainly try'd</l>
                     <l>All fair means, will not have recourse to foul.</l>
                     <l>And ravish that from her by force, which he</l>
                     <l>Cannot obtain by Love —</l>
                     <l>Ah how that fatall thought stirs up my fainting</l>
                     <l>Courage, and makes me resolve to act, what</l>
                     <l>I have too long defer'd —</l>
                     <l>This Barbarous Rivall he must die,</l>
                     <l>I'le sacrifice him to my Just revenge,</l>
                     <l>And though environ'd with millions of his guards</l>
                     <l>Yet I will force a passage to his heart —</l>
                     <l>"He that despiseth his own Life, is alwayes</l>
                     <l>Master of an others —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Honorius, <hi>and espies</hi> Justinianus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Just Heaven! I'st not an apparition</l>
                     <l>That deludes my senses, or can that be</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49923:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, am I awake? or do I dream?</l>
                     <stage>[Just. <hi>espies</hi> Hon.</stage>
                     <l>Can that be <hi>Honorius?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Ne're doubt if that you are <hi>Justinianus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But that I am <hi>Honorius.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me embrace my generous Friend — <hi>Embraces him.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis yet some comfort to me amidst all</l>
                     <l>My misfortunes, that Heaven grants me the</l>
                     <l>Happiness, again to see you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble <hi>Justinianus,</hi> my Joy is</l>
                     <l>So great, and so excessive, to see you</l>
                     <l>Alive, and safe, That I want Expressions</l>
                     <l>To utter it. And it makes me think that</l>
                     <l>Heaven has yet in store, some unexpected</l>
                     <l>Blessing for us, since after those many,</l>
                     <l>And confident reports of your death, I</l>
                     <l>Now find you living.</l>
                     <l>But, pray do me the favour as to relate</l>
                     <l>To me, by what strange fate you were preserv'd</l>
                     <l>From the ruins of that fatal day, in</l>
                     <l>Which we lost both our Prince, and Empire;</l>
                     <l>And in which it was reported that</l>
                     <l>You were slaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas by a fate as strange, as unexpected</l>
                     <l>But I desire your Pardon, if that first</l>
                     <l>I make inquiry, what information</l>
                     <l>You can give me concerning fair <hi>Irena:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For although I hear the <hi>Sultan</hi> treats her</l>
                     <l>Nobly, yet I cannot learn it but from</l>
                     <l>Persons, that are wholly at his devotion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>All that I can hear, either concerning</l>
                     <l>Your fair Mistriss, or my own, Is that they</l>
                     <l>Are both in the Palace, and that</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Perinthia</hi> is bestow'd of by</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan,</hi> to wait on your <hi>Irena.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>What is fair <hi>Perinthia</hi> your beautious</l>
                     <l>Mistris then in the Palace too, and</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Irena?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, so I hear, For by an Eunuch (whom</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49923:13"/>
                     <l>I have corrupted) I am inform'd that</l>
                     <l>She was this morning sent by the <hi>Sultan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As a Present to fair <hi>Irena.</hi> He</l>
                     <l>Further tells me that <hi>Irena</hi> uses</l>
                     <l>Often to walk in the Palace Garden.</l>
                     <l>And say's, he thinks she may walk there</l>
                     <l>This Evening, and take <hi>Perinthia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With her, which if she does the Eunuch ha's</l>
                     <l>Promiss'd to bring me word, and shew me</l>
                     <l>A way, that undiscover'd I may enter</l>
                     <l>In the Garden.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear Friend, do me the favour as to take</l>
                     <l>Me along with you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>I shall esteem my self most happy to</l>
                     <l>Enjoy your company, and fear no danger</l>
                     <l>Being so accompanied.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>But shall we not find out some way; and means</l>
                     <l>To free these Ladies from this Tyrants power?</l>
                     <l>Just now, I had design'd to go and kill</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan,</hi> in the midst of all his guards;</l>
                     <l>And either to have free'd <hi>Irena,</hi> or</l>
                     <l>Have perish'd in th' attempt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>What force had you to doe't?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just</speaker>
                     <l>None but my self.</l>
                     <l>Dispair, and the fear that he might offer</l>
                     <l>To her some violence, made me take that</l>
                     <l>Resolution.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Then <hi>Justinianus,</hi> Let me take leave</l>
                     <l>To tell you, that your design relish'd more</l>
                     <l>Of Fury and Dispair, then of true Valour,</l>
                     <l>And discretion. For suppose you had kill'd</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan,</hi> yet of necessitie, you</l>
                     <l>Must have perish'd.</l>
                     <l>And then you had left the fair <hi>Irena</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Behind, amidst a thousand dangers.</l>
                     <l>For who knows an if that you had slaine the</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan,</hi> to what danger you had expos'd her.</l>
                     <l>For let me tell you, 'Tis only his power.</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49923:13"/>
                     <l>That does protect her.</l>
                     <l>For the Bassa's and Souldiers, mad and incens'd</l>
                     <l>To see the Emperour thus to abandon</l>
                     <l>All his designs of enlarging of the</l>
                     <l>Empire, and to see him thus passionately</l>
                     <l>Dote on fair <hi>Irena;</hi> Talk that 'tis fit</l>
                     <l>He should be dispossest of the government,</l>
                     <l>And Throne, and that she should be offer'd up</l>
                     <l>A sacrifice to appease their fury.</l>
                     <l>But I have found out a way (less dangerous,</l>
                     <l>And more probable than yours) to free both</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi> and <hi>Perinthia</hi> from such danger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray, make me so happy as to acquaint</l>
                     <l>Me with it, and withall inform me how</l>
                     <l>You escap'd when the City was taken.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>I will You know, that fatal day in which</l>
                     <l>The City was lost, I was (by you as</l>
                     <l>Being General) commanded to defend</l>
                     <l>That quarter of the City assign'd by</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> for <hi>Zoganus</hi> to assault,</l>
                     <l>And which was distant far from yours.</l>
                     <l>Having long time defended it against</l>
                     <l>Their furious assault, and (if modesty</l>
                     <l>Permit me to say so) with success, For</l>
                     <l>Twice had they gain'd the top, And fixt their</l>
                     <l>Crescents on the wall, and twice were they beaten off.</l>
                     <l>In this condition were Affairs, when word</l>
                     <l>Was brought me, that you by reason of some</l>
                     <l>Wounds you had receiv'd were forc'd to retire,</l>
                     <l>And that in your absence, the <hi>Turks</hi> had forc'd</l>
                     <l>Your men to quit the breach, that you defended,</l>
                     <l>And were entring in the City. This news</l>
                     <l>So allarm'd me, that strait I drew off some</l>
                     <l>Of my chiefest men (though leaving behind</l>
                     <l>Me a number able to defend the</l>
                     <l>Wall against the Enemy) And marcht towards</l>
                     <l>The breach, with an intent to have regain'd</l>
                     <l>What we had lost.</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49923:14"/>
                     <l>But alas, I quickly found how impossible</l>
                     <l>It was to perform that Resolution,</l>
                     <l>For I found that the <hi>Turks</hi> were already</l>
                     <l>Enter'd in such numbers in the City,</l>
                     <l>That was impossible to expel 'em.</l>
                     <l>Which made me change my first design, and</l>
                     <l>Resolve to go and defend <hi>Perinthia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From their violence and fury.</l>
                     <l>But I found such a Panick fear possess</l>
                     <l>My men, and such a throng both of Souldiers,</l>
                     <l>And of People that fled, and the <hi>Turks</hi> so</l>
                     <l>Fast persuing e'm, that 'twas impossible</l>
                     <l>To perform what I had intended.</l>
                     <l>Grief, and dispair to see that all was lost,</l>
                     <l>Made me so careless of my self, that I</l>
                     <l>Having rallied together some few of</l>
                     <l>My Friends, I charg'd a whole body of the</l>
                     <l>Enemies, and despair made us fight so</l>
                     <l>Valiantly, that we put 'em to the rout.</l>
                     <l>But in that action I receiv'd so many</l>
                     <l>Wounds, that I fell down for dead:</l>
                     <l>And all my friends could do, was, to make a</l>
                     <l>Fair retreat, and carry off my body.</l>
                     <l>One of them propounded to carry me</l>
                     <l>To a house, of his scituated in a</l>
                     <l>Wood, some three Leagues distant from the City,</l>
                     <l>So conceal'd both by Art, and Nature, that</l>
                     <l>The Turks in all the time that they had lain</l>
                     <l>Before the City, could never find it out.</l>
                     <l>Thither having carried me, they search'd</l>
                     <l>My wounds, and found that though they would require</l>
                     <l>Long time for cure, yet they were not mortal.</l>
                     <l>'Twas there alas, I heard that sad and fatal</l>
                     <l>News, how that the Emperour had bin trod</l>
                     <l>To death i'the crowd, and that you were slain'd.</l>
                     <l>And though during the time my wounds retain'd</l>
                     <l>Me there, I frequently sent to see, if</l>
                     <l>I could learn any thing concerning fair</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49923:14"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Perinthia,</hi> what was become of her.</l>
                     <l>Yet I could never hear any thing that</l>
                     <l>Could assure me whether she were dead, or</l>
                     <l>Living.</l>
                     <l>Which made so deep an impression on my mind</l>
                     <l>And caus'd in me such a melancholly</l>
                     <l>That it much retarded the healing of</l>
                     <l>My wounds, But being at last recover'd,</l>
                     <l>I resolv'd to go to the City my self,</l>
                     <l>And try if Fortune would favour me more</l>
                     <l>Than she had done my messengers.</l>
                     <l>But 'twas so long before that I could hear</l>
                     <l>Any thing concerning <hi>Perinthia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That I began to despair of ere hearing</l>
                     <l>Of her.</l>
                     <l>Till at last 'twas my happy fate, the other</l>
                     <l>Day, by bribing of an Eunuch that belongs</l>
                     <l>To the Emperour's <hi>Seraglio,</hi> to</l>
                     <l>Hear <hi>Perinthia</hi> was there, and that</l>
                     <l>She had been taken prisoner when the</l>
                     <l>City was taken, and by reason of</l>
                     <l>Her beauty, presented to the <hi>Sultan,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who is so taken with fair <hi>Irena</hi>'s</l>
                     <l>Perfections, that he neglects all others.</l>
                     <l>You may imagine how I was overjoy'd</l>
                     <l>To hear this news, that she was alive, and</l>
                     <l>Safe, whom I had almost given over</l>
                     <l>Either for dead, or lost. But yet it was</l>
                     <l>Some mitigation to my joy, to hear</l>
                     <l>She was in the Seraglio; out of</l>
                     <l>Which I knowing it was impossible</l>
                     <l>By fair means to get her, resolv'd to do't</l>
                     <l>By force, and to deliver both <hi>Irena,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>An <hi>Perinthia</hi> from the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s power.</l>
                     <l>And having declar'd my design to my</l>
                     <l>Friends; I found 'em all ready to serve me</l>
                     <l>Both with their lives and fortunes.</l>
                     <l>And this night we have design'd to assault</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49923:15"/>
                     <l>The Palace, and, having freed <hi>Frena,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Perinthia,</hi> to make an escape</l>
                     <l>Into the Dominions of some Christian</l>
                     <l>Prince, and there (lest we might engage that State</l>
                     <l>In war) conceal both our names and persons.</l>
                     <l>This is the way I told you of, that I</l>
                     <l>Had found out to free our Mistresses from</l>
                     <l>Danger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot but both approve, and applaud</l>
                     <l>Your design as truly generous; and</l>
                     <l>Must confess 'tis both less dangerous and more</l>
                     <l>Probable to take effect, than mine.</l>
                     <l>But pray, What number may our Friends amount</l>
                     <l>To?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, about some five hundred, All stout, and</l>
                     <l>Valiant persons, having bin formerly</l>
                     <l>Most Officers under you: And if you</l>
                     <l>Please but to command us, and lead us on,</l>
                     <l>I doubt not the success.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>No Generous Friend that were to be</l>
                     <l>Injurious to you, and to deprive</l>
                     <l>You of the glory of the Action.</l>
                     <l>And though your General once, yet your heroick</l>
                     <l>Resolution to free <hi>Irena,</hi> obliges</l>
                     <l>Me now to be your servant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble <hi>Justinianus,</hi> you are oblig'd</l>
                     <l>By Honour to be our Chief. For 'tis not</l>
                     <l>Fit since you are alive, and safe, that any</l>
                     <l>Should have the glory to deliver fair</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena,</hi> but your self.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>If on that score my Honour be engag'd</l>
                     <l>Then yours <hi>Honorius</hi> is engag'd like mine;</l>
                     <l>Nor is it fit any should have the honour</l>
                     <l>To free the fair <hi>Perinthia,</hi> but your self.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Since then our honours are equally engag'd,</l>
                     <l>Let's equally participate in the</l>
                     <l>Glory. And since you'l not accept of the</l>
                     <l>Whole command, yet be pleas'd to be</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49923:15"/>
                     <l>My Partner.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you will have it so, I'le not contest.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Now <hi>Justinianus,</hi> I must beg your</l>
                     <l>Pardon, and leave you for some few minutes.</l>
                     <l>For just now, when I had the happy fortune</l>
                     <l>To find you, I was going to meet the</l>
                     <l>Eunuch, who is to meet me, and to bring</l>
                     <l>Me word, If that <hi>Irena</hi> and <hi>Perinthia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Walk this Evening in the Palace Garden.</l>
                     <l>But I fear I have trespass'd upon his</l>
                     <l>Patience, and made him stay too long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, let me not <hi>Honorius</hi> detain</l>
                     <l>You, from a business that so much concerns</l>
                     <l>Us both. But may not I go with you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot tell if't be convenient,</l>
                     <l>The Eunuch may perhaps be shie</l>
                     <l>To declare any thing to any but my self,</l>
                     <l>Till I've dispos'd him to it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>You are i'th right;</l>
                     <l>But when, and where shall I meet you again?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Meet me within this half hour without</l>
                     <l>The Western gate. And in the mean time I'le dispose</l>
                     <l>The Eunuch to grant you may go along with me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Well generous friend adieu,</l>
                     <l>I will not fail to meet you.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit.</hi> Hon.</stage>
                     <l>Fortune, be but propitious now, and kind,</l>
                     <l>And Poets never more shall feign thee blind.</l>
                     <l>But strait again they shall those Eyes restore</l>
                     <l>Which they so boldly took from thee before.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit.</hi> Just.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49923:16"/>
                  <head>Act. II. Scen. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Irena <hi>and</hi> Perinthia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Perinthia,</hi> I am so glad to see</l>
                     <l>You, that, if my misfortunes can admit</l>
                     <l>Of any Joy, 'tis to see you alive,</l>
                     <l>And safe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>And I <hi>Irena</hi> am so orejoy'd to</l>
                     <l>See you, That though Joy has bin long absent,</l>
                     <l>And a stranger to this breast, yet it now</l>
                     <l>Claims possession here.
<stage>Pointing at her breast.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> could never have made to me</l>
                     <l>A more acceptable Present, than when</l>
                     <l>He bestow'd you on me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas a happiness that fate had reserv'd</l>
                     <l>For me, in midst of all my misfortunes,</l>
                     <l>Which are so many, and so various,</l>
                     <l>That they surpass Expression —</l>
                     <l>Nor is it possible that I should be</l>
                     <l>Ever excell'd, I think in misery.</l>
                     <l>For surely 'tis beyond the power of fate,</l>
                     <l>Ere to make any so unfortunate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Perinthia,</hi> did I think it fit</l>
                     <l>My griefs could of comparisons admit,</l>
                     <l>The griefs which my oppressed heart endures</l>
                     <l>Not onely equals, but furpasses yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Can grief <hi>Irena</hi> in your breast have part</l>
                     <l>When you're possess'd of the great <hi>Sultan</hi>'s heart.</l>
                     <l>And he who does with fear the world surprize,</l>
                     <l>Yields himself captive to your conqu'ring Eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas <hi>Perinthia,</hi> 'tis against my mind,</l>
                     <l>That I the <hi>Sultan</hi> thus my captive find.</l>
                     <l>But did not you <hi>Justinianus</hi> know,</l>
                     <l>And the respect that gallant man I owe,</l>
                     <l>And what from me is to his merits due</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and th' affection too, he had for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49923:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Unkind <hi>Perinthia,</hi> Can you then suspect</l>
                     <l>That I should thus his memory neglect?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>'Love when the Object's absent, soon decay's;</l>
                     <l>But when once dead, seldom it lasts ten-dayes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Which of my Actions did you ever see,</l>
                     <l>Makes you suspect me of inconstancie?</l>
                     <l>No, no <hi>Perinthia,</hi> never think I can</l>
                     <l>Admit of Love; But for that generous Man.</l>
                     <l>And though he's dead, yet I will alway's strive</l>
                     <l>To keep him here, within my heart alive.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Your resolution Madam needs I must</l>
                     <l>Confess, is no less gen'rous than 'tis Just.</l>
                     <l>Pardon me Dear <hi>Irena,</hi> 'Twas not that</l>
                     <l>I suspected either your Vertue, or</l>
                     <l>Your Constancy, that I thus put you to</l>
                     <l>The trial, but only to be witness</l>
                     <l>Of that my self, which fame so much repor's</l>
                     <l>To your advantage.</l>
                     <l>And pray <hi>Irena,</hi> since that we have time,</l>
                     <l>And are alone, Do me the favour to</l>
                     <l>Acquaint me how first you came into the</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan</hi>'s power, and how he has since us'd</l>
                     <l>You: For although I've heard the same by fame related,</l>
                     <l>Yet she reports things so variously</l>
                     <l>That there's no credit to be given to</l>
                     <l>Her relations.</l>
                     <l>And since we've bin long absent, Let's relate,</l>
                     <l>What's yet unknown to us of either's fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray then do you begin.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>To comply with your desires, I will—</l>
                     <l>Since that you knew the affection the Brave</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Honorius</hi> bore me, I need not to declare</l>
                     <l>To you that that, is the sad cause of my</l>
                     <l>Misfortunes; you know that I had commands</l>
                     <l>By all my friends lai'd on me (as Persons</l>
                     <l>Extreamly desirous to see our Families</l>
                     <l>United) to use him with that civility,</l>
                     <l>And respect, which both his Birth, and Virtue</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49923:17"/>
                     <l>Claim'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>You had bin unjust, an if you had</l>
                     <l>Deny'd it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas, how needless were those Injunctions,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Honorius</hi> merits spoke so highly for</l>
                     <l>Him, that I must have bin ingrateful to</l>
                     <l>Have refus'd him the first place in my affections.</l>
                     <l>Nor was there any thing wanting to perfect</l>
                     <l>Our happiness, but onely the celebration</l>
                     <l>Of the Hymenaeal rites, which were to be</l>
                     <l>Perform'd within a few dayes:</l>
                     <l>When malicious Fate envying our prosperity</l>
                     <l>Sent the <hi>Sultan</hi> with an Army to besiege</l>
                     <l>This City.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Honorius</hi> thought he was oblig'd by</l>
                     <l>Honour to deprive himself of that happiness</l>
                     <l>(Which he said he should receive by my embraces)</l>
                     <l>As long as his Country was in danger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas a most Heroick resolution,</l>
                     <l>And worthy of Himself.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>You know that during the siege he behav'd</l>
                     <l>Himself so valiantly, that in that dismal day</l>
                     <l>In which the <hi>Sultan</hi> won the City, He</l>
                     <l>Had one of the most dangerous quarters</l>
                     <l>Committed to his trust, Which he defended</l>
                     <l>Bravely, till hearing of <hi>Justinianus</hi>'s</l>
                     <l>Misfortune, he attempted generously,</l>
                     <l>(though unfortunately to himself) to</l>
                     <l>Assist him. For in that action I was</l>
                     <l>Told (by one that saw him fall) my Dear <hi>Honorius</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Perisht.</l>
                     <l>Alas <hi>Irena!</hi> 'tis impossible</l>
                     <l>For me to express to you the grief which</l>
                     <l>The loss of this brave Person caus'd in my</l>
                     <l>Afflicted breast.</l>
                     <l>All those pangs and griefs that departing-souls indure,</l>
                     <l>Are nothing in comparison of what</l>
                     <l>I suffer'd, when first I heard this fatal</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49923:17"/>
                     <l>News, It so stupify'd me that it made</l>
                     <l>Me forget the sense and misery of</l>
                     <l>My own condition.</l>
                     <l>For when the City was won, I was made</l>
                     <l>Prisoner to an Officer, who fancying</l>
                     <l>Somthing of Beauty in me, Presented</l>
                     <l>Me to the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who strait commanded</l>
                     <l>Me to the Seraglio; where I have</l>
                     <l>Since remain'd, till yesterday the <hi>Sultan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Coming there to make choise of some to wait</l>
                     <l>On you; 'twas my happy fortune he judg'd</l>
                     <l>Me worthy of that honour, and by an</l>
                     <l>Eunuch sent me to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas a happiness transcended my expectations!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Now <hi>Irena,</hi> am not I truly miserable?</l>
                     <l>For can fate inflict a greater punishment</l>
                     <l>Than (by Death) to make an eternal divorce,</l>
                     <l>And seperation betwixt us, and the</l>
                     <l>Object of our Love.</l>
                     <l>And now methinks that Life seems tedious</l>
                     <l>To me, since I'm depriv'd of all that made</l>
                     <l>Me love it.</l>
                     <l>And from my breast Joy is for ever fled,</l>
                     <l>Since that my Dear <hi>Honorius</hi> now is dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Perinthia,</hi> 'tis sad what you relate,</l>
                     <l>I pitie and compassionate your fate.</l>
                     <l>For now I find by cruel fate's Decree</l>
                     <l>That our misfortunes in some sort agree.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>You see <hi>Irena,</hi> I've perform'd my part,</l>
                     <l>Let me now know what 'tis afflicts your heart.</l>
                     <l>For when we know what is each others grief,</l>
                     <l>Perhaps we may each other give relief.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Although that relation will but renew</l>
                     <l>My griefs, yet 'tis but Justice I should keep</l>
                     <l>My promise. —</l>
                     <l>You know, <hi>Perinthia,</hi> that my Father, Prince</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Theodosius,</hi> finding that it had not</l>
                     <l>Pleas'd Heaven to bless him with any male.</l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49923:18"/>
                     <l>Issue, but that all the hopes of our now</l>
                     <l>Almost-extinct Family surviv'd in me,</l>
                     <l>Made it his chiefest care to see me match'd</l>
                     <l>Into some Noble Family, and to</l>
                     <l>Some Person that in his judgment might not</l>
                     <l>Be unworthy of me.</l>
                     <l>And having with a careful eye survey'd</l>
                     <l>Those Persons whom either Birth, or Merits</l>
                     <l>Might make pretenders to me, found none,</l>
                     <l>So worthy to enjoy that Title as</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus,</hi> A Person whose vertues,</l>
                     <l>And merits were as eminent, as his</l>
                     <l>Birth was illustrious, being neerly ally'd</l>
                     <l>In several respects to the Imperial</l>
                     <l>Family; And who for some Victories lately</l>
                     <l>Obtain'd against the Empires Enemies,</l>
                     <l>Was, at the age of four and twenty years,</l>
                     <l>Made Generalissimo by the Emperour,</l>
                     <l>And highly in his favour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Perin.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas but what was due to his deserts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>On this brave person my Father resolv'd</l>
                     <l>To bestow me; the rather too, because</l>
                     <l>He had heard, that he had long secretly</l>
                     <l>Affected me.</l>
                     <l>It is not easie to represent to</l>
                     <l>You how I was overjoy'd, when I found</l>
                     <l>My Father's judgment, agree with my choice.</l>
                     <l>For I had long before yielded up my heart</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Justinianus</hi>'s high merits.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Or else you had bin ungrateful.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing now was wanting, but the Nuptial</l>
                     <l>Ceremonies to compleat our felicitie.</l>
                     <l>When perverse Fate (as a Prologue to my</l>
                     <l>Future miseries) took away my Father:</l>
                     <l>Who before he died made the Emperour</l>
                     <l>My Guardian, and with his last breath commanded</l>
                     <l>Me ne're to marry any, but</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49923:18"/>
                     <l>The Emperour (after he had allow'd</l>
                     <l>Me to dry up those tears which Nature</l>
                     <l>Did require for the loss of so neer a</l>
                     <l>Relation) mindful of the promise which</l>
                     <l>He had made my dying Father, resolv'd</l>
                     <l>To celebrate the marriage;</l>
                     <l>When Fate again, resolv'd to cross</l>
                     <l>Our happiness, seiz'd <hi>Justinianus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With a violent disease, and during</l>
                     <l>His sickness the Emperour was</l>
                     <l>So unfortunate, as to lose all those</l>
                     <l>Advantages which he had gain'd before.</l>
                     <l>And the <hi>Sultan</hi> persuing his good fortune,</l>
                     <l>Came and besieg'd this City.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus,</hi> now at length recover'd,</l>
                     <l>Long time couragiously defended the</l>
                     <l>City 'gainst their fury; till at last,</l>
                     <l>You know, the Enemy having made a</l>
                     <l>Breach in the wall, resolv'd to give a general</l>
                     <l>Assault. <hi>Justinianus</hi> long time defended</l>
                     <l>The breach bravely, till at length having receiv'd</l>
                     <l>Several wounds, he was forc'd to retire.</l>
                     <l>But hearing that th' Enemy in his absence</l>
                     <l>Had gain'd the breach, he again return'd, and</l>
                     <l>Having long fought valiantly, at length opprest</l>
                     <l>With numbers, was forc'd to fall a Sacrifice</l>
                     <l>To their revenge.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas when I heard it, how did I deplore</l>
                     <l>The loss of that gallant Person!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Perinthia,</hi> it surpasses my expression</l>
                     <l>To relate to you with what grief I receiv'd</l>
                     <l>This fatal news: Let it suffice to tell</l>
                     <l>You, that grief so seiz'd on all my senses</l>
                     <l>That I immediately fell into a swound.</l>
                     <l>But O Heaven, how was I amaz'd, when</l>
                     <l>I came to my self, to see a Souldier</l>
                     <l>With his sword drawn enter into my Chamber!</l>
                     <l>Who approaching the Bed whereon I lay,</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49923:19"/>
                     <l>Took me up in his arms; which action, together</l>
                     <l>With his fierce aspect, so frighted me, that</l>
                     <l>I fell into a second swound.</l>
                     <l>But imagine Dear <hi>Perinthia,</hi> with what</l>
                     <l>Amazement I was strook, when returning</l>
                     <l>Again to life, I found my self in a</l>
                     <l>Strange place, and saw none neer me, but three or</l>
                     <l>Four rude Souldiers. But the grief that I conceiv'd</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Justinianus</hi>'s Death was so great,</l>
                     <l>That I was insensible of my own danger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas <hi>Irena,</hi> how I pity the</l>
                     <l>Condition you were then in!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>The Souldier at first (as I understood</l>
                     <l>By their whisp'ring) had a design t' attempt</l>
                     <l>My Honour, but being ore'rul'd by his</l>
                     <l>Companions perswasions (who guest me of</l>
                     <l>Some quality) and the hopes of a reward,</l>
                     <l>Resolv'd to present me to the <hi>Sultan.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Next day (for 'twas then late) they resolv'd to</l>
                     <l>Put their Design in execution; and carrying me</l>
                     <l>With e'm, presented me to the <hi>Sultan,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who being then imploy'd in State-affairs,</l>
                     <l>Sent me by an Eunuch to the <hi>Seraglio;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where I continued about a moneth, till</l>
                     <l>One day sending for me to his presence,</l>
                     <l>He pretended to find in me those perfections,</l>
                     <l>Which I want, and somthing that pleas'd his fancy.</l>
                     <l>And since protests that we have changed conditions,</l>
                     <l>And that he is become my captive, and my slave.</l>
                     <l>And uses me (to do him Justice) with</l>
                     <l>All civility, and respect, In hopes</l>
                     <l>To gain my affection. But <hi>Justinianus</hi>'s</l>
                     <l>Image, and the sense of what I ow his</l>
                     <l>Memory, is so deeply imprinted in</l>
                     <l>My heart, that 'tis impossible that I</l>
                     <l>Should ere affect any other.</l>
                     <l>For though he's Dead, yet he retains that part,</l>
                     <l>Which Living, he had alway's in my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49923:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>By what that you relate, alas I find,</l>
                     <l>Fortune has bin to both alike unkind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Our fates have such similitude, that we</l>
                     <l>Are both ally'd by Love, and Destiny.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>In other ills we may hope for a cure,</l>
                     <l>But here we must continually indure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet let us patiently to Heaven submit,</l>
                     <l>And let's resign to what the Fates think fit.</l>
                     <l>'Tis our duty, Perhaps the Pow'rs above</l>
                     <l>Will grant us ease by Death, though not by Love.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus II. Scena III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Osman, <hi>and</hi> Murat.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osm.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Murat,</hi> I fear I shall a Prophet prove,</l>
                     <l>And that that black Cloud, which has long hung ore</l>
                     <l>Our heads, will now at last dissolve into</l>
                     <l>A sudden Storm.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Murat.</speaker>
                     <l>What in probabilitie can be else</l>
                     <l>Expected, For we have receiv'd Orders</l>
                     <l>From our Bassa to be ready this night</l>
                     <l>To assault the Palace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>And we too, have receiv'd the like Orders from our Aga.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Murat.</speaker>
                     <l>I could wish it were otherwise, and that</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Sultan</hi> could be reclaim'd by other means,</l>
                     <l>Less violent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>I could wish so too; but there are few of</l>
                     <l>Our opinion, for the Janizaries.</l>
                     <l>And Souldiers are all so insenc'd with the</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultans</hi> late weaknesses, that it is an eafie</l>
                     <l>Matter for the Bassa's, to blow up those</l>
                     <l>Sparks of discontent quickly into a flame,'</l>
                     <l>The more easily to obtain their own ambitious</l>
                     <l>Ends.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Murat</speaker>
                     <l>I pitie the Empire's sad condition,</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49923:20"/>
                     <l>And hope, Fate will yet prevent our ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Osman.</speaker>
                     <l>I, so do I too. 'But 'tis wisdom to</l>
                     <l>Bear that patiently, which is not in our</l>
                     <l>Power to prevent.</l>
                     <l>'Those hopes are vain, we to our selves create,</l>
                     <l>When they resist, what is decreed by Fate.
<stage>Excunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. III. Scen. I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet <hi>and</hi> Irena.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>When, fair <hi>Irena,</hi> shall I pity find,</l>
                     <l>Will you be alwayes cruelly incli'nd?</l>
                     <l>Shall pity never in your breast have part,</l>
                     <l>Will you then wound, and never cure my heart?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas how you mistake, that is in me</l>
                     <l>Vertue, which you it seems call Cruelty.</l>
                     <l>And it is far beyond my pow'r I'm sure,</l>
                     <l>To cure those wounds, which you say you endure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis strange, that you whose radiant Eyes thus have</l>
                     <l>The pow'r to kill, should want the pow'r to save.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>What you attribute to my Eyes, is more</l>
                     <l>Than ere I knew that they could do before.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>You cannot sure, but needs must know their pow'r,</l>
                     <l>When they enslave new hearts thus every hou'r.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>An if they do, 'tis not by any Skill,</l>
                     <l>Or Art I use; 'tis much against my will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Nature alas in you has too much part,</l>
                     <l>That you should be beholding unto Art.</l>
                     <l>But shall not I your heart to pity move,</l>
                     <l>Since 'tis impossible to gain your love?</l>
                     <l>Shall I ner'e find that pity which I want?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Why do you ask that which I cannot grant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, what is't that hinders you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Honour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Honour, why, that is but a vain, and</l>
                     <l>Emptie word, And far too weak, If you consent</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49923:20"/>
                     <l>To hinder my felicity.</l>
                     <l>Divine <hi>Irena,</hi> do but you prove kind</l>
                     <l>And I will take that scruple from your mind.</l>
                     <l>I'le make you my <hi>Sultana,</hi> you shall be</l>
                     <l>Both Mistress of the prostrate World, and Me.</l>
                     <l>And in the Empire you shall have a part.</l>
                     <l>Equal to that, which you have in my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>If such rewards you'l give then you may find,</l>
                     <l>Objects more worthy, and perhaps more kind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>No, there is none to whom such honor's due,</l>
                     <l>Unless <hi>Irena,</hi> that it be to you.</l>
                     <l>Compar'd to you, all other Beauties seem,</l>
                     <l>Objects not fit, nor worthy my esteem.</l>
                     <l>Fair <hi>Irena,</hi> do but ease me o'those</l>
                     <l>Pains (which for your sake I endure) and I</l>
                     <l>Will bestow my Throne upon you, and make</l>
                     <l>You sole Empress o' the world.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm not ambitious, Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah Madam, Do but think who 'tis that asks</l>
                     <l>Your pity. 'Tis he that doth command the world,</l>
                     <l>And on whose frown or smile the world's fate depends,</l>
                     <l>As his does now on yours.</l>
                     <l>Nor do I take any Joy in the spacious</l>
                     <l>Empire I possess, and to see my self</l>
                     <l>So great a Monarch, But onely that I</l>
                     <l>May be the more worthy to enjoy the</l>
                     <l>Title of fair <hi>Irena</hi>'s servant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Prince, it misbecomes my State to have</l>
                     <l>Such Servants, and 'tis a Title too unworthy</l>
                     <l>For you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a Title Madam, that I'm more proud</l>
                     <l>Of, than all my former Conquests.</l>
                     <l>Divine <hi>Irena,</hi> do but consider</l>
                     <l>How miserable I am like to be,</l>
                     <l>If that you deny to compassionate my</l>
                     <l>Sufferings. For since that first I receiv'd</l>
                     <l>Your coelestial Image i' my heart,</l>
                     <l>Your divine perfections has made such an</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49923:21"/>
                     <l>Impression on my mind, that there's nothing</l>
                     <l>In the world, which in my esteem</l>
                     <l>I vallue equivolent to your own fair Self.</l>
                     <l>All what was formerly dear unto me,</l>
                     <l>As Empire, and desire of Glory, seems</l>
                     <l>Now things below my estimation.</l>
                     <l>All my ambitious desires tend now</l>
                     <l>To gain your Love. And, should you deny me</l>
                     <l>That happiness, you'd make me for ever</l>
                     <l>Miserable.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas, it lies not in my power: I hope</l>
                     <l>You'l be more wise than so to settle your</l>
                     <l>Affection, on such an unworthy Object.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Irena,</hi> wrong not your own Beauty so,</l>
                     <l>To say the Object is unworthy.</l>
                     <l>Nature when she form'd you, resolv'd to shew</l>
                     <l>Us her Master-piece, And bestow'd on you</l>
                     <l>All that she hath of Excellence, and all</l>
                     <l>That may be wish'd for in a Woman.</l>
                     <l>For all those perfections, which she has confus'dly,</l>
                     <l>And disorderly bestowed on others,</l>
                     <l>Meet all in you, as in their Center.</l>
                     <l>And in your fair Eyes, she has plac'd a vivacity,</l>
                     <l>And lustre that far excels all others.</l>
                     <l>And methinks the Sun, when in it's height of Glory,</l>
                     <l>Seems dull unto those brighter Beams shot from</l>
                     <l>Your beauteous Eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I see, you're pleas'd to Complement,</l>
                     <l>There's no such brightness, nor lustre i'my Eyes,</l>
                     <l>Nor am I Mistris o'those perfections,</l>
                     <l>Which you attribute to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>No, what I speak is real —</l>
                     <l>You're Mistris of so many perfections,</l>
                     <l>That they exceed my relation.</l>
                     <l>Nature's too blame, she form'd you with such Art,</l>
                     <l>In your fair breast, to place a cruel Heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49923:21"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter an</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
                     <l>Without, Great Sir, the Bassa <hi>Mustapha</hi> waits,</l>
                     <l>And humbly craves that he may be admitted</l>
                     <l>Into your sacred Presence;</l>
                     <l>And say's, he has a Secret to reveal,</l>
                     <l>Which from all others he must yet conceal.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>What should this mean—</l>
                        <l>Surely it must be o'some consequence,</l>
                        <l>Else hee'd not be thus importunate.</l>
                        <l>And he was ever faithful —</l>
                     </lg>
                     <l>Tell him, that he should stay a little,</l>
                     <l>And I'le come to him strait.
<stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Madam, you see for some time I must leave</l>
                     <l>You; But when I return again, I hope</l>
                     <l>I shall find you in a better humour:</l>
                     <l>And hope you'll then accept, when next we meet</l>
                     <l>Of th' Empire, I now prost rate at your feet.
<stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Mahomet. <hi>manet</hi> Irena.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Irena <hi>sola.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> thinks, that Empire I admire,</l>
                     <l>That I'm ambitious, and a Throne desire.</l>
                     <l>But he shall find that those his hopes are vain,</l>
                     <l>And that I can his profer'd Throne disdain.</l>
                     <l>Empire's a charm too weak to work on me,</l>
                     <l>When I'm resolv'd to keep my Loyaltie.</l>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Justinianus,</hi> I yet too well know</l>
                     <l>What 'tis that to your memorie I owe,</l>
                     <l>Ere to give leave Ambition here should rest,</l>
                     <l>And to admit a Monster in my breast,
<stage>Pointing to her breast.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>For your dear sake, I can with ease despise</l>
                     <l>Those flatt'ring glories offer'd to my eyes.</l>
                     <l>And though I must confess, Our sex is frail,</l>
                     <l>And Greatness somtimes does with us prevail;</l>
                     <l>Yet, I resolve, though I a woman bee,</l>
                     <l>That I'le preserve my Loyalty to thee.</l>
                     <l>And let this be an Argument to move</l>
                     <l>Men to believe, Our Sex can constant prove.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49923:22"/>
                  <head>Act. III. Scen. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Justinianus, <hi>and</hi> Honorius, <hi>In the Palace Garden.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>So the Eunuch has perform'd his part, and</l>
                     <l>We are I think, enter'd undiscover'd in</l>
                     <l>The Garden.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>I wonder, <hi>Irena</hi> and <hi>Perinthia</hi> are not here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis yet soon,</l>
                     <l>This is the time, and this the place in which</l>
                     <l>The Eunuch told us they would walk</l>
                     <l>This Evening —</l>
                     <l>But stay, I hear some noise —
<stage>Hears a noise.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Perhaps they're coming, Let's retire behind
<stage>They retire behind some hedges.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>These hedges, till we make further discov'ry.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Irena <hi>and</hi> Perinthia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Did the <hi>Sultan,</hi> Madam, offer you his Throne,</l>
                     <l>And were you so generous to refuse it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes <hi>Perinthia,</hi> what could I do less?</l>
                     <l>I was oblig'd both by Love and Honour</l>
                     <l>To refuse it. For I resolve to keep</l>
                     <l>A firm, and inviolable constancy</l>
                     <l>To the memory of my dear <hi>Justinianus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor will I ere give cause for to mistrust</l>
                     <l>But that I'le to his memory prove just.</l>
                     <l>And though he's dead, yet his memory</l>
                     <l>Keeps too strong possession i'my heart,</l>
                     <l>That I should ere admit an other there.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Fortune, for this I thank thee, I cannot
<stage>He speaks this from behind the hedge.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be truly miserable, if she continues</l>
                     <l>Constant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49923:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Irena,</hi> I grow emulous</l>
                     <l>O' your Vertue.—</l>
                     <l>To refuse a Crown, when freely offer'd</l>
                     <l>Only to observe a Punctilio</l>
                     <l>Of Love, and Constancy, to a Person</l>
                     <l>Who is dead (and consequently out of</l>
                     <l>A capacity, ere to give you thanks)</l>
                     <l>Is an action so Heroick, and so</l>
                     <l>Generous, that I believe your Vertue may</l>
                     <l>Find many admirers, but few imitators.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope that my example will be a means</l>
                     <l>To stir up others, on the like occasion,</l>
                     <l>To be my Imitators.</l>
                     <l>Would not you <hi>Perinthia,</hi> an if the</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan</hi> should offer you, what he does me,</l>
                     <l>And on the like conditions, refuse it</l>
                     <l>To preserve your Loyaltie to</l>
                     <l>Your <hi>Honorius?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes <hi>Irena,</hi> I would not onely (like you)</l>
                     <l>Refuse, and reject with disdain, the Throne</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> should offer me; But, like you,</l>
                     <l>Resolve ever to preserve my affection</l>
                     <l>Constant to my <hi>Honorius.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>How happy am I i'this Ladies affection
<stage>He speaks this aside, &amp; from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the hedge.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I did ever believe her generous,</l>
                     <l>But this transcends imagination:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I see <hi>Perinthia,</hi> that Love, and Gratitude</l>
                     <l>Equally ballances our thoughts;</l>
                     <l>And that we have an equal sence, of what</l>
                     <l>We ow their memories.</l>
                     <l>What would I give, that now their generous souls,</l>
                     <l>Had knowledge o'th constant affection</l>
                     <l>We still bear 'em?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>An if that it be true that Souls</l>
                     <l>Departed from their bodies, have knowledg</l>
                     <l>Of what happens here below, I doubt not</l>
                     <l>But they know how constant we are to 'em.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah, that Heaven would but permit that their</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49923:23"/>
                     <l>Souls might now from their blest abodes</l>
                     <l>But come, and visit us; methinks 'twould be</l>
                     <l>Some mitigation to our misfortunes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>That would but disturb the rest, and tranquillity</l>
                     <l>Their pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ef souls do now enjoy, and but</l>
                     <l>Serve to affright us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Now <hi>Honorius,</hi> is our time,
<stage>
                           <hi>They come from behind the hedges, and present themselves to</hi> Ire. <hi>and</hi> Per.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let's discover our selves.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>But Heaven what is't I see —
<stage>They espy them.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Am I awake — or do I dream—</l>
                     <l>Or am I in Elizium!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>O ye Coelestial Powers, sure you've heard</l>
                     <l>My prayers, and sent their Ghosts to visit us.</l>
                     <l>What's ere thou art, that thus com'st to disturb us,
<stage>To Just.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Th'ast taken such a pleasing form, and shape</l>
                     <l>Upon thee, and so void of horror, that</l>
                     <l>I cannot be affrighted.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, be not deceiv'd, we are no Ghosts,</l>
                     <l>But Persons preserv'd by Heaven for your</l>
                     <l>Deliverance.</l>
                     <l>We are really <hi>Justinianus</hi> and <hi>Honorius.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah, sure it cannot be —</l>
                     <l>The blessing is too great, and too improbable</l>
                     <l>To be real —</l>
                     <l>I fear 'tis some Illusion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, 'tis no Illusion, but real</l>
                     <l>What you see, we were by Heaven preserv'd</l>
                     <l>From those ruines, which you think overwhelm'd</l>
                     <l>Us, and were not slain (as you imagine)</l>
                     <l>When the City was taken.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Can it then be that my <hi>Honorius</hi> lives?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Perinthia,</hi> can it be that Fate</l>
                     <l>Grants me again the happiness to see</l>
                     <l>You, after so long a separation?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah my <hi>Honorius,</hi> Heaven now rewards</l>
                     <l>Me for all those griefs and miseries, which</l>
                     <l>The report o' your death caus'd in</l>
                     <l>My afflicted breast.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49923:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>And all those torments which your loss,</l>
                     <l>And separation caus'd in me are now</l>
                     <l>Forgotten, since now again I see you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>The Joy that I conceive is now so great</l>
                        <l>That it transcends Expression—</l>
                        <l>And it so fills my breast, 'tis past allay,</l>
                        <l>I know not what to do, nor what to say.</l>
                        <l>Joy so transports me, that it strikes me mute;</l>
                        <l>No Language can with such a passion sute.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Justinianus,</hi> tell me by what strange</l>
                     <l>Means, that you escap'd; I cannot conceive</l>
                     <l>It to have bin less than miraculous.</l>
                     <l>Come, Pray begin—</l>
                     <l>I am impatient till that you relate,</l>
                     <l>What there is yet of hidden i'your Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, your commands (like Oracles) it</l>
                     <l>Were impious to disobey.</l>
                     <l>You know Madam, that unhappy day in</l>
                     <l>Which the City was taken, I undertook</l>
                     <l>To defend the Breach the Enemy had</l>
                     <l>Made i'th wall:</l>
                     <l>And that in its defence, having receiv'd</l>
                     <l>Many wounds, and lost much blood, I was forc'd</l>
                     <l>(More through my friends perswasions, than my own</l>
                     <l>Inclination) to retire.</l>
                     <l>But alas, I had soon cause to curse that</l>
                     <l>Resolution.</l>
                     <l>For my men as long as I was with 'em</l>
                     <l>Had defended the breach bravely, and out-done</l>
                     <l>Belief: But as soon as I was gone (possest</l>
                     <l>With a belief that my wounds were mortal)</l>
                     <l>They turn'd their backs, and fled.</l>
                     <l>I was quickly advertiz'd of this disaster.</l>
                     <l>And too soon (though too late to prevent it)</l>
                     <l>Saw the folly I had committed.</l>
                     <l>Rage, and dispair so possest me, that I</l>
                     <l>Had scarce patience to stay till that my wounds</l>
                     <l>Were bound up, But that I would return, to</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49923:24"/>
                     <l>See if things were in that desperate condition</l>
                     <l>They were represented to me.</l>
                     <l>But alas, I found the danger greater</l>
                     <l>Than I imagin'd. I found such swarms</l>
                     <l>Of Turks enter'd in the Breach, that it was</l>
                     <l>Impossible to save the Town.</l>
                     <l>having got together as many Souldiers,</l>
                     <l>As the confusion, and disorder things</l>
                     <l>Were then in, would permit me, and being</l>
                     <l>Neer the Palace, I went directly thither;</l>
                     <l>To know what was become of the Emperour;</l>
                     <l>But there 'twas told me he was fled, but none</l>
                     <l>Knew whither.</l>
                     <l>From thence Madam (Love being predominant</l>
                     <l>O're all my other passions) I resolv'd</l>
                     <l>To go, and defend you; But I found such</l>
                     <l>A number of Turks in my way, that it</l>
                     <l>Was not in my power to perform what</l>
                     <l>I had resolv'd, and I quickly found that</l>
                     <l>I was incompass'd on all sides, so that</l>
                     <l>It was impossible to escape.</l>
                     <l>My men (to whom despair added new courage)</l>
                     <l>Fought it out bravely, and fell most before</l>
                     <l>My face, and at last weakned with wounds and</l>
                     <l>Loss of blood, I was forc'd my self to fall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes <hi>Justinianus,</hi> I heard you fell,</l>
                     <l>But bravely, and like your self;</l>
                     <l>But pray, proceed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Towards Evening the Turks fell to stripping</l>
                     <l>The dead Bodies, And 'twas my happy fate</l>
                     <l>To be stript by a Janizary, who</l>
                     <l>(Being more charitable than generally</l>
                     <l>Those kind of persons are) finding some symptoms</l>
                     <l>Of life yet remaining in me, and guessing</l>
                     <l>Me by my habits, to be of no inferiour</l>
                     <l>Quality, resolv'd if possible to save</l>
                     <l>My life; and carrying me to his quarters</l>
                     <l>(He himself having some skill in Chirurgery)</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49923:24"/>
                     <l>Search'd my wounds, and finding that although</l>
                     <l>They were deep, and many, yet none were mortal,</l>
                     <l>He us'd means to bring me to my self, which</l>
                     <l>He soon effected.</l>
                     <l>But how was I amaz'd, when returning</l>
                     <l>To my Senses, I found my self in a bed,</l>
                     <l>In a strange place, and my wounds bound up!</l>
                     <l>I soon call'd to remembrance what was past,</l>
                     <l>And the grief which I conceiv'd for the danger</l>
                     <l>I apprehended you were in, and to</l>
                     <l>See my self a Prisoner, made such a violent</l>
                     <l>Impression on my mind, that (if I had</l>
                     <l>Not bin hinder'd) I would have torn</l>
                     <l>Up my wounds.</l>
                     <l>The Janizary, apprehending that</l>
                     <l>My dispair proceeded from the belief</l>
                     <l>I had, that I had lost my Liberty,</l>
                     <l>Told me, 'Twas true, by right of war I was</l>
                     <l>His prisoner; but promis'd me, that, as soon</l>
                     <l>As I was cur'd, he would give me my liberty,</l>
                     <l>And set me free; which he accordingly</l>
                     <l>Perform'd.</l>
                     <l>I was much pleas'd to find such humanity</l>
                     <l>In a Barbarian. I ask'd him if</l>
                     <l>He could tell me any-tidings of the</l>
                     <l>Emperour, or of you Madam. He told</l>
                     <l>Me, that as yet he could not tell any-thing</l>
                     <l>Of the Emperour; And for you, he said</l>
                     <l>He did not know you, and was ignorant</l>
                     <l>Who you were. But he promis'd me he would</l>
                     <l>Make inquiry. Next day he went out, and when</l>
                     <l>He return'd, he brought me word that the Emperor</l>
                     <l>Was slain; But said of you he could hear no</l>
                     <l>News.</l>
                     <l>But ah, how did this fatal News afflict</l>
                     <l>Me! how did I curse my self for being</l>
                     <l>The cause of these disasters, and for retiring</l>
                     <l>From the Breach!</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49923:25"/>
                     <l>Grief so seiz'd on me, that it much hindred</l>
                     <l>The healing o'my wounds, and much prolong'd</l>
                     <l>My cure, which I think the Janizary</l>
                     <l>Had scarce ever effected, had not I</l>
                     <l>Heard that you had bin presented to the</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan,</hi> and that you were in the Palace, and were safe.</l>
                     <l>'Twas only the hope I had by some means or other,</l>
                     <l>To free you from the <hi>Sultans</hi> power, made</l>
                     <l>Me submit to those means that were us'd for</l>
                     <l>My recovery.</l>
                     <l>I heard what a Passion he has for you,</l>
                     <l>And though your Vertue secur'd me, that I</l>
                     <l>Did not doubt a change i' your affections;</l>
                     <l>Yet I was affraid that he might use force,</l>
                     <l>And offer you some violence; which thoughts</l>
                     <l>Much distracted, and perplext my mind.</l>
                     <l>As soon as I was recover'd, I try'd</l>
                     <l>To give you notice I was living;</l>
                     <l>But I found that impossible, your Guards</l>
                     <l>Were too vigilant, and too faithful to be</l>
                     <l>Corrupted, and I could find none whom I</l>
                     <l>Durst trust.</l>
                     <l>I made diligent inquiry to see</l>
                     <l>If I could hear what was become of you</l>
                     <l>
                        <stage n="*">
                           <hi>To</hi> Hon.</stage> Brave Friend,
<stage n="*">
                           <hi>To</hi> Per.</stage> and of you Madam: But could ne'r</l>
                     <l>Hear what was become of either of you</l>
                     <l>Till to day it was my happy fortune</l>
                     <l>To meet with <hi>Honorius,</hi> who told me,</l>
                     <l>Fair <hi>Perinthia,</hi> you were here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Honorius</hi> sure has good intelligence</l>
                     <l>To have notice of it so soon. For I</l>
                     <l>Was but this morning sent by the <hi>Sultan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To <hi>Irena.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas by an Eunuch Madam that waits on</l>
                     <l>You, that I was inform'd of it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus</hi> before you proceed further,</l>
                     <l>Clear me of two Doubts which possess me.</l>
                     <l>And first pray tell me, how you, two, whose faces</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49923:25"/>
                     <l>Are so well known i'this City, can walk</l>
                     <l>About the streets undiscover'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>When we walk about the streets Madam, we</l>
                     <l>Have disguises, which to that purpose we</l>
                     <l>Alwayes carry about us.</l>
                     <l>Besides, our death has bin so confidently</l>
                     <l>Reported, that none suspects us living.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>You've clear'd me of the one, now clear me of</l>
                     <l>The other; How could you conceal your self</l>
                     <l>From the Janizary? did not he in</l>
                     <l>All the time you were with him demand your</l>
                     <l>Name?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes he did often, and was very inquisitive</l>
                     <l>To know who I was, But I alwayes conceal'd</l>
                     <l>My true name and quality from him,</l>
                     <l>And put him off with some feign'd story.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>You've satisfy'd my curiositie,</l>
                     <l>Pray go on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah Madam, 'tis beyond expression to</l>
                     <l>Relate to you all those torments, which your</l>
                     <l>Absence and separation caus'd i'my</l>
                     <l>Troubled breast —</l>
                     <l>There was no Grief, no Passion to which I</l>
                     <l>Was not subject to.</l>
                     <l>But now since I've again the happiness</l>
                     <l>To enjoy your presence, all my griefs and</l>
                     <l>Sufferings are buried in oblivion.</l>
                     <l>Like as the Sun (long absent) at last breaks</l>
                     <l>Through a Cloud, and with its rayes both comforts</l>
                     <l>And enlightens all the lower world;</l>
                     <l>And by its splendid Beams chases away</l>
                     <l>Dark Clouds and Mists, and makes a glorious day:</l>
                     <l>So your fair Eyes whose radiant Beams excel</l>
                     <l>The others brightness, quickly doth expel</l>
                     <l>Those Clouds of Grief, and sadness which dwelt here,
<stage>Pointing to his breast.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>But which now vanish, since that you appear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus,</hi> I am glad to find</l>
                     <l>My Eyes has yet such influence o're your mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49923:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>In a heart Madam, that once yields its self</l>
                     <l>Their Captive, they alwayes keep possession—</l>
                     <l>But I'le proceed—</l>
                     <l>Fortune, I think, now at last weary with</l>
                     <l>Tormenting me, resolves again to make</l>
                     <l>Me happy. For 'twas my good fortune</l>
                     <l>This day, by a happy, and unexpected Fate</l>
                     <l>To meet with my generous Friend <hi>Honorius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(Whom I thought dead) who told me that he had</l>
                     <l>Contriv'd and design'd a brave and generous</l>
                     <l>Resolution, to restore you to your</l>
                     <l>Liberties, having to that end made</l>
                     <l>A Combination with all his Friends this</l>
                     <l>Night to assault the Palace; And</l>
                     <l>By force to free you from the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s power.</l>
                     <l>And that he might give you notice of his</l>
                     <l>Design, he has corrupted an Eunuch</l>
                     <l>That attends you, who told us that you would</l>
                     <l>Walk here this Evening, and shew'd us a way</l>
                     <l>That we might enter undiscover'd</l>
                     <l>I' the Garden.</l>
                     <l>And hither we are come to know, if you'll</l>
                     <l>Be pleas'd to condescend to what, that we</l>
                     <l>Resolve to execute.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes <hi>Justinianus,</hi> you've my consent;</l>
                     <l>I think your design to be noble, and</l>
                     <l>Generous, and worthy the affection you</l>
                     <l>Alwayes profest to bear us.</l>
                     <l>Nor do I think it can reflect upon</l>
                     <l>Our Honours, for us to trust our selves to</l>
                     <l>The conduct of Persons, whom all our Friends</l>
                     <l>Design'd to be our Husbands.</l>
                     <l>And I dare engage, <hi>Perinthia</hi>'s thoughts</l>
                     <l>Agrees with mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>You may Madam; I repose such</l>
                     <l>A confidence in <hi>Honorius</hi>'s vertue,</l>
                     <l>That I dare follow him throughout the world.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, I hope I shall ne'r give you cause</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49923:26"/>
                     <l>By any of my Actions for to lose</l>
                     <l>The good Opinion you have of me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>But <hi>Justinianus,</hi> Pray tell me, an if</l>
                     <l>Your enterprize (as I hope it will) succeeds;</l>
                     <l>Whither will you conveigh us? what retreat</l>
                     <l>Have you chosen? For doubtless the <hi>Sultan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Will cause diligent search to be made for</l>
                     <l>Us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, we have a Vessel i' the Port</l>
                     <l>That there waits for us, ready to convey</l>
                     <l>Us into the Dominions of some Christian Prince.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>And there, If you please to consent; we will</l>
                     <l>Conceal both our Names and Persons, Lest we</l>
                     <l>Might draw the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s revenge upon that</l>
                     <l>State.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I like your Counsel well,</l>
                     <l>And think 'tis best we follow it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus,</hi> 'Tis time that we withdraw.</l>
                     <l>The time now draws neer that I appointed</l>
                     <l>To meet my generous Friends.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>When you will, I'le wait on you—</l>
                     <l>Madam, we have appointed to meet those</l>
                     <l>Friends we have engag'd in our design, to</l>
                     <l>Consult about the Action we are to</l>
                     <l>Perform this night, and now the hour draws neer,</l>
                     <l>So that we must be forc'd (though much against</l>
                     <l>Our wills) to depart; But if you please to</l>
                     <l>Do us the favour to meet us here within this</l>
                     <l>Two hours, we'll wait on you again, and take some further</l>
                     <l>Resolution, concerning our Escape.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, we'll not fail to meet you,</l>
                     <l>'Tis best you now depart, for although these</l>
                     <l>Walks be so secret, yet to stay here too long,</l>
                     <l>Is unsafe, and there might be danger in't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, we must now take our leaves,</l>
                     <l>Within two hour's well not fail to</l>
                     <l>Wait on you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor we to meet you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:49923:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>My Dear <hi>Honorius,</hi> adieu.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah how rigid would this parting seem,</l>
                     <l>Were I not in hopes quickly to return!</l>
                     <l>Adieu my dear <hi>Perinthia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt</hi> Just. <hi>&amp;</hi> Hon.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>You see <hi>Perinthia,</hi> things have chang'd their face.</l>
                     <l>'Tis good our ills with patience to embrace.</l>
                     <l>The Fates are pleas'd you see, when we resign,</l>
                     <l>And do submit to what that they design.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a reward sent from the Pow'rs above</l>
                     <l>Because we were so constant in our Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, Let's go in, and pray those Pow'rs to bless</l>
                     <l>Their Enterprize, And crown it with success.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. III. Scen. III.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Aga.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>I fear this <hi>Mustapha</hi> will discover</l>
                     <l>Our design, And then should it not succeed</l>
                     <l>I am lost for ever—</l>
                     <l>Who know's what influence the <hi>Sultans</hi> presence</l>
                     <l>May have upon the Souldiers —?</l>
                     <l>The Guards told me they went this way, and alone;</l>
                     <l>I le follow, and endeavour to hear their discourse.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet, <hi>and</hi> Mustapha.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>What villains are these Bassa's, did you represent</l>
                     <l>To 'em the hainousness o' their crime?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Great Sir, I did,</l>
                     <l>And us'd all those Arguments which I thought</l>
                     <l>Might be conducive to disswade 'em from</l>
                     <l>Their treacherous resolution.</l>
                     <l>But alas, I found 'twas vain;</l>
                     <l>Rebellion had taken too strong possession</l>
                     <l>I' their breasts, and chac'd Loyalty from thence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Does the cause of this their Conspiracy</l>
                     <l>(Which seems so monstrous, and so Gyant-like)</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:49923:27"/>
                     <l>Proceed from th' affection I have for</l>
                     <l>Fair <hi>Irena?</hi> Is that the cause on't?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>That is the pretence—</l>
                     <l>Traytors never want a pretence</l>
                     <l>'To colour their Designs;</l>
                     <l>And that which encourages 'em to execute</l>
                     <l>Their Treachery, Is that they know</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers and People (alwayes severe</l>
                     <l>Censurers of their Prince's actions) are</l>
                     <l>Displeas'd and incens'd to see you lay by</l>
                     <l>All thoughts o'f inlarging o'the Empire;</l>
                     <l>And thus passionately to affect the</l>
                     <l>Fair and beauteous <hi>Irena,</hi> whom they</l>
                     <l>Imagine to be the cause of that alteration</l>
                     <l>They have lately observ'd i'your Heroick nature.</l>
                     <l>And therefore threaten her destruction,</l>
                     <l>And to sacrifice her to their revenge,</l>
                     <l>And have resolv'd that she shall die —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven! what is't I hear, <hi>Irena</hi> die—</l>
                     <l>Dare such base slaves threaten her precious life?</l>
                     <l>Was ever such a villany invented—</l>
                     <l>But I'le provide tortures, and torments for 'em</l>
                     <l>Black, and horrid as their crimes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Let not, great Prince, Passion over-rule</l>
                     <l>Your reason. Consider if—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>What should I consider—</l>
                     <l>Should I let these villains assault my Palace,</l>
                     <l>And by force ravish my Mistris from out</l>
                     <l>My arms, And tamely suffer the affront?</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Mustapha,</hi> Patience were here</l>
                     <l>No Vertue, but a Crime.</l>
                     <l>They shall all die—</l>
                     <l>Their Lives are too poor a sacrifice to</l>
                     <l>Appease my anger, and to expiate</l>
                     <l>Their offence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Aga <hi>and conceals him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Great <hi>Sultan,</hi> do but Consider if it</l>
                     <l>Is in your pow'r to act, what you design.</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers and People are all at their</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:49923:28"/>
                     <l>Devotion, and I suspect your Guards too:</l>
                     <l>For the <hi>Aga</hi> is the chief Fomenter,</l>
                     <l>And Agent in this Conspiracie.</l>
                     <l>'Tis he that is the wheel that gives motion</l>
                     <l>To all the rest.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>I thought this villain would nominate me:
<stage>Aside.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>How bravely he sets me forth!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I have long suspected him for a knave.</l>
                     <l>The Office I have bestowed upon him.</l>
                     <l>Has made him too proud, and too ambitious.</l>
                     <l>He I resolve shall die—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Shall I so—</l>
                     <l>But I'le prevent my ruine with your own.
<stage>Aside.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>But <hi>Mustapha,</hi> is't not strange that</l>
                     <l>These perfidious slaves dares be so audacious</l>
                     <l>As to censure any o' my Actions;</l>
                     <l>And to accuse me of Vices they are</l>
                     <l>Themselves possest of.</l>
                     <l>Does it become them (my slaves and vassals)</l>
                     <l>To intermeddle, and condemn</l>
                     <l>Their Prince's Actions?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>'Princes actions are alwayes expos'd to Censure.</l>
                     <l>Persons, the higher they are elevated</l>
                     <l>In qualitie, the more their actions are</l>
                     <l>Observ'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true—</l>
                     <l>Subjects behold their Princes faults</l>
                     <l>Through a Multiplying-glass, which makes 'em</l>
                     <l>Seem far greater then they are.</l>
                     <l>But what way shall I find out to stop this</l>
                     <l>Breach, before it be too wide?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas, I fear 'tis grown too wide already,</l>
                     <l>And that 'tis now past remedy.</l>
                     <l>I know but one way left t' appease their fury;</l>
                     <l>But I fear you'll think the remedy, worse</l>
                     <l>Than the disease.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>What is't? speak freely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49923:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis my Loyalty (Majestick <hi>Sultan</hi>)</l>
                     <l>And your Command, makes me so bold to tell</l>
                     <l>You, That I think there is no other remedy</l>
                     <l>Left to appease their fury, but by your</l>
                     <l>Forsaking of <hi>Irena.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Forsake <hi>Irena</hi>—What <hi>Mustapha,</hi> would you</l>
                     <l>Counsel me to an action so unjust?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Necessity makes actions Just.</l>
                     <l>'Tis just, Because 'tis necessary.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Would you have me expose <hi>Irena</hi> to</l>
                     <l>Their fury—No, I'le first perish, and let</l>
                     <l>The Empire sink, before that I'le perform</l>
                     <l>So degenerous an action.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas great Sir, you misapprehend,</l>
                     <l>And misconstruct my meaning: I would not</l>
                     <l>Have you expose <hi>Irena</hi> to their fury;</l>
                     <l>But have you to conquer your own affection</l>
                     <l>Let it not be said, that He who</l>
                     <l>Has conquer'd so many Kingdoms,</l>
                     <l>Could not subdue a foolish Passion.</l>
                     <l>And though at first it may seeme hard, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,</l>
                     <l>Yet Time (the common Physician to all</l>
                     <l>Diseases) will at length afford you cure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Irena</speaker>
                     <l>is a Beautie, from whose charms,</l>
                     <l>You'l be better preserv'd by absence, then</l>
                     <l>By resistance. And your Souldiers, an if</l>
                     <l>They be not imploy'd abroad, will imploy</l>
                     <l>Themselves at home. 'Tis idleness, and want</l>
                     <l>Of Martial discipline that makes 'em now</l>
                     <l>Thus insolent.</l>
                     <l>Follow the example of your illustrious</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Othoman</hi>-Ancestors, And lead 'em again</l>
                     <l>Forth, to enlarge your Empire, and to obtain</l>
                     <l>New Conquests. Make it appear—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49923:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mustapha,</hi> no more: I don't approve your</l>
                     <l>Counsell—Their fury must be allay'd by</l>
                     <l>Other means, than those which you propounded.
<stage>Kneels.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>If in ought, Great Prince, I have offend</l>
                     <l>You, I humbly beg your pardon.</l>
                     <l>'Twas my Loyaltie, and your Danger, made</l>
                     <l>Me take the Libertie t' express my thoughts</l>
                     <l>Thus freely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Although it be dang'rous for Subjects to</l>
                     <l>Intermeddle i'their Prince's Affairs,</l>
                     <l>Yet your Loyaltie has obtain'd your pardon.</l>
                     <l>Rise <hi>Mustapha,</hi> and follow me.
<stage>He rises.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>I must go studie, to find out some way,</l>
                        <l>This their Rebellious Furie to allay.</l>
                        <l>'Tis easier far Rebellions to prevent,</l>
                        <l>Than in their heat to hinder their intent.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Mahomet, <hi>&amp;</hi> Mustapha: <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> Aga.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49923:29"/>
                  <head>Actus III. Scena IV.</head>
                  <stage>Aga <hi>solus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>So, 'tis well I was here to hear this their</l>
                     <l>Discourse. I thought what it would come to,</l>
                     <l>And that this <hi>Mustapha</hi> would discover</l>
                     <l>Our Design to the <hi>Sultan,</hi> none else</l>
                     <l>I knew durst do't — If it succeeds, 'tis well;</l>
                     <l>If not, then what becomes of me? My death's</l>
                     <l>Resolv'd already!</l>
                     <l>"Ills when known, may be prevented;</l>
                     <l>But are most dang'rous, when we are</l>
                     <l>Ignorant of 'em.</l>
                     <l>"Rocks, and shelfs hid under water</l>
                     <l>"Deceive the skilful'st Pilots.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> hath resolv'd my Death; But I</l>
                     <l>Resolve, his death shall secure my life.</l>
                     <l>"Self-preservation is a Principle infus'd</l>
                     <l>"By Nature in our hearts, as soon as we</l>
                     <l>"Are born.</l>
                     <l>My safetie, and Revenge, Ile joyn together.</l>
                     <l>I have long labour'd to be reveng'd for</l>
                     <l>The affront the <hi>Sultan</hi> did me, when he</l>
                     <l>Bestow'd on <hi>Mustapha</hi> a place that was</l>
                     <l>Promis'd me, and that was due only to</l>
                     <l>My merits. And Fortune now furnishes</l>
                     <l>Me with occasions to second my desires.</l>
                     <l>'Tis that, makes me so eagerly to</l>
                     <l>Stir up the Bassa's, and Souldiers</l>
                     <l>To Rebellion.</l>
                     <l>"The <hi>Sultan</hi> now shall find how dangerous 'tis</l>
                     <l>"For Princes to be ungrateful.</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:49923:30"/>
                     <l>For by his Death, which I resolve, I'le strive</l>
                     <l>To be reveng'd, and save my self alive.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. IV. SCEN: I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MY mind is so perplext with care, and grief,</l>
                        <l>That I had need of all my courage</l>
                        <l>To sustain the weight of my misfortunes:</l>
                        <l>Yet, 'tis not the apprehension I have</l>
                        <l>For my own, But for the fair <hi>Irena</hi>'s</l>
                        <l>Danger, that thus abates my courage.</l>
                        <l>How ill somtimes do Princes place their favours!</l>
                        <l>I have raiz'd these Villains to that height, they</l>
                        <l>Now dare attempt to pull me from my Throne.</l>
                        <l>Perfidious slaves, cannot I affect</l>
                        <l>The fair <hi>Irena;</hi> but must they envie</l>
                        <l>My felicitie, and threaten her destruction?</l>
                        <l>Ah, how it torments me, to think I have</l>
                        <l>No power, nor can find out no way to be</l>
                        <l>Reveng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d, or to hinder their treacherous</l>
                        <l>Intentions.</l>
                        <l>To forsake <hi>Irena!</hi> alas, 'tis impossible,</l>
                        <l>But if it were not, I'd rather perish,</l>
                        <l>Than to be guilty of so black a Crime,</l>
                        <l>As to expose this Soul-in-chanting Fair-one</l>
                        <l>To their fury.</l>
                        <l>To lose my Empire, and to be depriv'd</l>
                        <l>Of the Fruit of all my Conquests, by such</l>
                        <l>Perfidious Villains, does not a little</l>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:49923:30"/>
                        <l>Trouble me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor can my Fancy, as yet, find out means</l>
                        <l>To help me out of two such great Extreams.</l>
                        <l>To lose <hi>Irena,</hi> then my Love is crost;</l>
                        <l>And if I lose my Empire, I am lost.</l>
                        <l>Such ills as these, my mind does so amuze,</l>
                        <l>I know not yet, Which of these ills to chuse.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Love, and Ambition agitates my mind</l>
                        <l>With equal Fury, And like to two</l>
                        <l>Impetuous winds, when they meet together</l>
                        <l>I'the Ocean, Each strives for mast'ry.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>State-Int'rest say's, Ambition here should sway
<stage>Pointing to his breast.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>But Honour say's, That Love I should obey.</l>
                        <l>For I'm oblig'd by Honour to protect</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Irena,</hi> though she does my Love neglect.</l>
                        <l>Love gains the field in this contentious strife;</l>
                        <l>'Ile save <hi>Irena,</hi> or I'le lose my life.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49923:31"/>
                  <head>Act. IV. Scen. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Carazias, Zoganus, Caly-Bassa, <hi>Mahometes, and the</hi> Aga <hi>of the Janizaries.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Generous Friends, I find you have bin zealous</l>
                     <l>I'th' Empires cause, And that by your endeavours</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers are all unanimously agreed</l>
                     <l>T' assault the Palace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>We've perform'd our Duty,</l>
                     <l>And are now resolv'd to make th' Empire an</l>
                     <l>Amends, that we've suffered so effeminate</l>
                     <l>A Prince to govern it so long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>And to recover the Glory we've lost.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>But shall we dispossess the <hi>Sultan</hi> of</l>
                     <l>His Throne—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, what else? Do you think it can be safe</l>
                     <l>For us (after we've perform'd what we intend)</l>
                     <l>To leave him in a capacity to</l>
                     <l>Revenge himself of the affront which he</l>
                     <l>Conceives we do him. No, we must</l>
                     <l>Not only deprive him of the Government,</l>
                     <l>But too secure his Person.</l>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>I must not tell them, that I mean to kill him,</l>
                        <l>That would betray my malice, and revenge.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>Have you sent Prince <hi>Bajazet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Notice of our Design.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>No, 'Tis time enough after its</l>
                     <l>Execution.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>But how an if he should reject what we</l>
                     <l>Propound, And refuse the Throne we offer</l>
                     <l>Him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Refuse it—No, he's not such a fool.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Othoman</hi>-Princes are too desirous</l>
                     <l>Of Sov'raigntie, to refuse a Throne</l>
                     <l>When offer'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49923:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>But what's become of <hi>Mustapha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where's he?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Why he has bin with the <hi>Sultan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"To discover to him our Design; From whom,</l>
                     <l>"If it succeeds not, we must expect</l>
                     <l>"The worst effects of Fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>I ever doubted, <hi>Mustapha</hi> would prove</l>
                     <l>A villain, and discover our Design.</l>
                     <l>But 'tis no matter as long as we have force</l>
                     <l>To execute what we resolve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>And let's not now delay it.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> now knows of our Design,</l>
                     <l>And will endeavour to prevent it.</l>
                     <l>And if he should present himself to the</l>
                     <l>Souldiers (from whom he has bin long absent)</l>
                     <l>Who knows what effects his Presence</l>
                     <l>Might produce?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>That seems improbable.</l>
                     <l>He knows the Souldiers are discontented,</l>
                     <l>And breathe nothing, but fury, and revenge.</l>
                     <l>I do not think he'll be so vent'rous—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Not be so vent'rous —</l>
                     <l>What danger is there his courage dares not</l>
                     <l>Venture on?</l>
                     <l>Have we not seen him run head-long into</l>
                     <l>Dangers, as great as this?</l>
                     <l>"Despair makes Cowards valiant,</l>
                     <l>And will it not, think you, rouze up</l>
                     <l>His sleeping courage?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zoga.</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps it may—</l>
                     <l>But do you think we shall find resistance?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>From none, but from some of his domestick</l>
                     <l>Servants, The Guards are all at my Devotion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>If we shall find such small resistance,</l>
                     <l>And since the Guards will give us free access.</l>
                     <l>What need we assault the Palace, with such</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49923:32"/>
                     <l>Numbers?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis necessary to shew that 'tis not</l>
                     <l>An action of our own; But that the whole</l>
                     <l>Army is consenting.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis best I think that we' go first</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Irena</hi>'s Lodgings, and offer her</l>
                     <l>Up a Victim to the Empires safetie.</l>
                     <l>That done, Let's secure the <hi>Sultans</hi> person.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>You counsel wisely —</l>
                     <l>Night with her sable curtains</l>
                     <l>Does now ore-spread the Air,</l>
                     <l>'Tis now time that we put our Design</l>
                     <l>In execution.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Actions of this Nature, the sooner they're</l>
                     <l>Perform'd, the better; and the safer.</l>
                     <l>Let's not now defer it any longer;</l>
                     <l>All things are now in readiness, and the</l>
                     <l>Souldiers only want our presence</l>
                     <l>To countenance the action.</l>
                     <l>Should we but delay it, they might lose that</l>
                     <l>Eagerness and fury of revenge that we've</l>
                     <l>Inspir'd into 'em.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>No, come; Let's go,</l>
                     <l>Before their conrage cools.</l>
                     <l>Delay's are dang'rous—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>But where shall we meet</l>
                     <l>To joyn our Troops together?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Where — Why in the open place</l>
                     <l>Before the Palace. No place</l>
                     <l>Is more convenient.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>And in what time?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Why? within an hour at furthest.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, without fail, I'le meet you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>And so will I.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor will I fail.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor I—</l>
                     <l>But are you sure the Guards will give us access?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49923:32"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, for that I'le engage,</l>
                     <l>Lave that to my care. But come let's go.</l>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>So, things go well as yet, and Fate conspires</l>
                        <l>To second my intention, and desires.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. IV. Scen. III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet <hi>and</hi> Irena.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam be ruled, Let's fly, and let's not stay,</l>
                     <l>Lest that we perish by our own delay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>What gen'rous <hi>Sultan,</hi> can you fly, and yield,</l>
                     <l>When y'are a Conquerour, to slaves the field?</l>
                     <l>Where's now your courage, that you can allow</l>
                     <l>These slaves to snatch the Lawrel from your brow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>My courage faints, and dares not now appear:</l>
                     <l>But 'tis for you, not for my self I fear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Take care to save your Self, and as for me,</l>
                     <l>Leave that to Fate, and my own Destinie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave you <hi>Irena!</hi> no, that cannot be;</l>
                     <l>If you miscarry, What becomes of me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, is't upon my Fate, that you intend</l>
                     <l>Your safetie, or your ruine, should depend?</l>
                     <l>Should I miscarry, yet the loss is small;</l>
                     <l>But if You lose your Empire, you lose all.</l>
                     <l>Therefore once more, Let me the favour crave</l>
                     <l>You'd take less care for me, more That to save.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah, think not that my thoughts are so abject,</l>
                     <l>That, to save That, I should my Love neglect.</l>
                     <l>'Tis not my Empires loss causes my grief,</l>
                     <l>If I lose that, my Sword can give relief.</l>
                     <l>New Empires I can gain, but not subdue</l>
                     <l>The grief, and passion that I have for you.</l>
                     <l>'Tis Love, not Empire, has the greatest part</l>
                     <l>In all the grief that now afflicts my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Ambition only in your heart should rest,</l>
                     <l>'Tis a fit passion for a Monarch's breast.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:49923:33"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Though I have Love, yet I've Ambition too,</l>
                     <l>But 'tis not to gain Empire, but gain You.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi> is a Beauty so Divine,</l>
                     <l>I'd freely part with all, to make her mine.</l>
                     <l>But Heav'n! what is't I say, when Fate denies</l>
                     <l>That I am worthy such a glorious prize?</l>
                     <l>For she's above my merits; I can gain,</l>
                     <l>Nor pretend nothing from her, but disdain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi> is unworthy to have part</l>
                     <l>In (or possess) so great a Monarch's heart.</l>
                     <l>And though you're pleasd to think that she's above,</l>
                     <l>Yet she's too low an Object for your Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>What Object is there i'the world, that's higher</l>
                     <l>To which that my ambition can aspire?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>To Glory and Renown, and to obtain</l>
                     <l>What may to you immortal Honour gain;</l>
                     <l>Those are fit Objects, and are worthy you:</l>
                     <l>But let not Love your gen'rous heart subdue.</l>
                     <l>Your Face shew's that y'are troubled, I suspect</l>
                     <l>That 'tis not Love, but Fear does you deject.</l>
                     <l>For shame let not your Slaves rebellious pow'r</l>
                     <l>Deprive you of your Conquests in an hour;</l>
                     <l>And let not that by Treason be undon,</l>
                     <l>Which you by many Victories have won.</l>
                     <l>Call up your courage, and forbear to give</l>
                     <l>These slaves such pow'r, But still a Monarch live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>What a Heroick Spirit here does rest,</l>
                        <l>And is contain'd within this Lady's breast?</l>
                        <l>Sure, she's my Better-Genius that is sent,</l>
                        <l>Mine, and my Empires ruine to prevent.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <l>Your Courage, and your Beautie I admire;</l>
                     <l>Each equally my breast with Love inspire.</l>
                     <l>But Madam, you mistake, that is not Fear</l>
                     <l>Which on my Visage now seems to appear.</l>
                     <l>Danger could never yet my heart surprize,</l>
                     <l>Were you but safe, I could with ease despise</l>
                     <l>These Bassa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s threats; My courage is above</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49923:33"/>
                     <l>All other dangers, but th'assaults of Love.</l>
                     <l>Wou'd you prove kind, I cou'd my Throne defend,</l>
                     <l>And make my fate upon my sword depend.</l>
                     <l>And wou'd you but accept what is your due,</l>
                     <l>I'd then defend it, to bestow't on you.</l>
                     <l>To neglect what you scorn, how can I chuse?</l>
                     <l>You both my Person, and my Throne refuse.</l>
                     <l>Were I so happy, that you would but give</l>
                     <l>Me yet some comfort, I'd a Monarch live:</l>
                     <l>The malice of my Stars, I'd then defie,</l>
                     <l>And on <hi>Irena</hi> for my Fate rely.</l>
                     <l>Then Madam, see that you have pow'r alone</l>
                     <l>To make me happy, and to save my Throne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>It is beyond my pow'r to effect</l>
                     <l>What you imagine, or your Throne protect.</l>
                     <l>You speak as if I'd pow'r to create</l>
                     <l>Some new Decrees, or alter those of Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis not the Fates, But your fair Eyes that be</l>
                     <l>The only Rulers of my Destinie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I now begin to pity you, 'Tis Love</l>
                     <l>I see that makes your Reason thus to rove:</l>
                     <l>It is a Passion too unworthy you,</l>
                     <l>"A generous mind Love ought not to subdue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet Love's a Passion we too often find,</l>
                     <l>That lodges most within a gen'rous mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true: But 'tis our own consent, and will,</l>
                     <l>That makes us subject to so great an ill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah, 'tis not in our choice, but 'tis above</l>
                     <l>Our pow'r to hinder the decrees of Love.</l>
                     <l>We oftentimes our selves know not the cause,</l>
                     <l>Why we are subject to his rigid Law's.</l>
                     <l>"To resist his Decrees is vain, Love's darts</l>
                     <l>Can quickly force Obedience from our hearts.</l>
                     <l>No humane pow'r is able to withstand</l>
                     <l>Against the pow'r and force of Love's command.</l>
                     <l>But Madam, I must now again renew</l>
                     <l>My late request, and that Design persue.</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:49923:34"/>
                     <l>He that ne're us'd to ask, does now implore</l>
                     <l>You'd mind your danger, and your safetie more:</l>
                     <l>And once again intreats you (since the night</l>
                     <l>Will favour us) not to delay our flight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Danger persues those that do from it fly</l>
                     <l>Let's stay, and let's on our own Fates rely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, be not so obstinately bent</l>
                     <l>To your own ruine, thus to give consent.</l>
                     <l>I've told you of the danger you are in,</l>
                     <l>But must not now commit so great a sin</l>
                     <l>As grant your stay, That were but to expose</l>
                     <l>You to the rage, and fury of your foes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, do you think our flight can make us free</l>
                     <l>From what's decreed for us by destiny.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>No, "But again, we ought not to neglect</l>
                     <l>"Those means our selves, Heav'n gives, us to protect.</l>
                     <l>When Nature is distemper'd, we then chuse</l>
                     <l>Physitians help, and not their aid refuse.</l>
                     <l>And since th'approaching danger is so near,</l>
                     <l>Give him that does adore you leave to fear:</l>
                     <l>And though you will not flie, yet grant, I may</l>
                     <l>Conceal your Person, to secure your stay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>That may prolong my pain not cure the wound;</l>
                     <l>If you miscarry, I shall soon be found.</l>
                     <l>No, if my ruine be by Heav'n decreed</l>
                     <l>That cannot hinder, but it must succeed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>If then to neither you will give consent,</l>
                     <l>Your ruine I must other-wayes prevent.</l>
                     <l>Since to my Counsel you no ear afford,</l>
                     <l>I'le strive for to protect you by my Sword.</l>
                     <l>Then Madam come, I must at once secure</l>
                     <l>You, and my self, from what we might indure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49923:34"/>
                  <head>Act. IV. Scen. IV.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Perinthia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>What strange confusion's here, what new alarms</l>
                     <l>Does make the Souldiers thus to be in Arms?</l>
                     <l>All's so disorder'd, as if Fate resolv'd</l>
                     <l>The world should now to Chaos be dissolv'd.</l>
                     <l>It seems so horrid, and so strange to me,</l>
                     <l>I can't imaginewhat the cause should be:</l>
                     <l>Unless (which Heav'n I hope will yet prevent)</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> has discover'd our intent.</l>
                     <l>Just Heav'n forbid, such Fate should us attend,</l>
                     <l>Grant our mis-fortunes now may have an end.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Irena.</stage>
                     <l>But here's <hi>Irena;</hi> since she does appear</l>
                     <l>She'll soon dispel, or soon increase my fear.</l>
                     <l>Ah Madam! You come in a fit time to</l>
                     <l>Resolve me of those Doubts which now perplex]</l>
                     <l>My breast.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>What is't, <hi>Perinthia,</hi> troubles you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas, I fear we are undone;</l>
                     <l>And that envious Fate has to the <hi>Sultan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Discover'd our Design.</l>
                     <l>But Madam, You I know can soon declare,</l>
                     <l>If we have cause to hope, or to dispair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>As yet we've cause to hope;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> knows nothing of it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>What's the reason then, that the Guards are all</l>
                     <l>In Arms, and that there's such a Confusion</l>
                     <l>'I the Palace, and things so out of Order.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, it seems the Bassa's and Souldiers,</l>
                     <l>Enrag'd to see the <hi>Sultan</hi> doat on me,</l>
                     <l>And to neglect all his former Designs,</l>
                     <l>Have conspir'd against him, and resolve to</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:49923:35"/>
                     <l>Deprive him of his Throne, and me of my</l>
                     <l>Life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>What treacherous Rascals are these Bassa's?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>This Design the <hi>Sultan</hi> came just now to</l>
                     <l>Acquaint me with, and to counsel me either</l>
                     <l>By flight, or by concealment to avoy'd</l>
                     <l>Their Furie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>And which have you chosen Madam?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Neither.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>What, Dear <hi>Irena,</hi> do you then Resolve?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>To stay Madam, and rely upon the promise</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Justinianus</hi> and <hi>Honorius.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For should I either flie, or conceal my self,</l>
                     <l>I should deprive them of their expectation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Why Madam, should you for that, be accessary</l>
                     <l>To your own danger? Perhaps this Design</l>
                     <l>May prevent theirs. Cannot you fly, and give</l>
                     <l>Them notice of your retreat: Methinks this</l>
                     <l>Should be a means to escape both from the</l>
                     <l>Sultan and Bassa's.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>It might, could the <hi>Sultan</hi> be perswaded</l>
                     <l>To stay behind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>What, Madam? Will he go with you, and leave</l>
                     <l>His Empire a prey to his Rebellious Subjects?</l>
                     <l>Cannot the Power you have over him</l>
                     <l>Perswade him to the contrarie?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>No, but suppose it could, whom have I that</l>
                     <l>I durst have trusted to acquaint <hi>Justinianus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With my retreat; For had I consented,</l>
                     <l>I should have bin forc'd to have departed</l>
                     <l>Instantly away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, if that were all, I would have don't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Yo've don't? No, dear <hi>Perinthia,</hi> had I gon,</l>
                     <l>You must have gone along.</l>
                     <l>Or else it wou'd but have perplext my mind,</l>
                     <l>Should I have gone, and left you here behind:</l>
                     <l>What comfort could I have enjoy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d in my</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:49923:35"/>
                     <l>Own security; If you had bin expos'd</l>
                     <l>To danger. But to prevent that, and not</l>
                     <l>To disappoint <hi>Justinianus,</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(Whom we've engag'd to meet) I have</l>
                     <l>Endeavour'd to inflame the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s breast</l>
                     <l>With Honour and Revenge. Hoping that whil'st</l>
                     <l>He persues the preservation of his</l>
                     <l>Empire, I shall have more libertie to enjoy</l>
                     <l>My self, and facilitate our escape.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>You've done discreetly Madam, and I hope</l>
                     <l>That same Providence that has preserv'd us</l>
                     <l>From so many dangers will still watch over us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>We have no reason to mistrust it.</l>
                     <l>Since Heav'n has already (as an earnest</l>
                     <l>Of our future happiness) granted that</l>
                     <l>We have found those Persons living, whom we</l>
                     <l>Thought dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Fortune has long bin cruel, but I trust</l>
                     <l>It will prove kind at last, and now be just.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>If their Design (on which that I rely)</l>
                     <l>Succeeds, I dare its Malice then defie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope it will, and hope that these Bassa's</l>
                     <l>Rebellion, will serve to further, and not</l>
                     <l>To hinder their Design. For in the disorder,</l>
                     <l>And confusion things are now in, it will be</l>
                     <l>An easie matter to escape: And the</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan</hi> will be otherwise imploy'd than</l>
                     <l>To make persuit after us.</l>
                     <l>I hope, things will succeed better then we</l>
                     <l>Expect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I wish they may—</l>
                     <l>Fortune, and Love, I hope will both combine</l>
                     <l>To aid, and second that which we design,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>They're two blind Pow'rs, or else if they could see,</l>
                     <l>To favour us, then they would soon agree.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Cause is just. And though they have no eyes,</l>
                     <l>Yet they have Justice, they are Dieties.</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49923:36"/>
                     <l>'Twere impious to think ought else could rest</l>
                     <l>Or find a place in a Coelestial breast.</l>
                     <l>But come, the Time is not yet expir'd</l>
                     <l>In which we appointed to meet 'em;</l>
                     <l>Let's retire into the next room, and sing;</l>
                     <l>Or else by too much reflecting on our</l>
                     <l>Present condition, I shall grow melancholy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>What you think fit, I must consent to.</l>
                     <stage>They retire into the next room, and sing.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Song.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Coelestial Pow'rs that rule above,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And that incline our hearts to Love,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Since you've bin cruel, now be kind,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And grant that we some ease may find.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Grant that our hearts opprest with grief</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>May now at length find some relief.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fair</hi> Paphian <hi>Queen, to whose bright eyes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Gods themselves became a prize:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ah, Let's intreat thee, pray thy Son</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To finish what he has begun.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For Love's a flame that may grow less,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If not recruited by success.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Great God of Love, whose pow'rful Dart</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>At once wounds both the Mind, and Heart:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ease us from what we still indure,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From future storms, let's be secure:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And we'll proclaim Love then to be</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of all the greatest Dietie.</hi> ‖</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>The Song ended, they enter again.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>So now, I think 'tis time that we retire,</l>
                     <l>Delay perhaps might make our Hopes exspire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:49923:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope not so: of its success by Heav'n,</l>
                     <l>We have already some assurance giv'n.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>If Fate proves kind, then it will soon dispel</l>
                     <l>Those fears, which in our troubl'd breasts now dwell.</l>
                     <l>But dear <hi>Perinthia</hi> come, I fear we may</l>
                     <l>Make things succeed amiss, by our delay.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. IV. Scen. V.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm lately grown so wretched, that the more</l>
                     <l>I think on my condition, I deplore</l>
                     <l>My own misfortunes; and they are so new,</l>
                     <l>I cannot yet imagine they are true,</l>
                     <l>But think 'tis some <hi>Chimaera</hi> form'd by night,</l>
                     <l>Which only serv's my senses to affright.</l>
                     <l>To day when Glorious <hi>Phoebus</hi> rose, he saw</l>
                     <l>The world without controul receive my Law.</l>
                     <l>None durst dispute, nor, then, none durst withstand,</l>
                     <l>But all obey'd, to what I did command.</l>
                     <l>I then was happy, had Fate but supprest</l>
                     <l>Those Flames of Love, which still torment my breast;</l>
                     <l>Or had <hi>Irena</hi> prov'd but kind, and cur'd</l>
                     <l>Me of those pains, which for her I indur'd.</l>
                     <l>To perfect my felicity, the aid</l>
                     <l>Was only wanting of that beautious Maid.</l>
                     <l>But now I'm made so wretched by my Fate,</l>
                     <l>That I'm scarce known for what I was of late.</l>
                     <l>Strange changes i'my fate, there is begun,</l>
                     <l>Betwixt the rising, and the setting Sun.</l>
                     <l>But these complaints are womanish in me,</l>
                     <l>Revenge would with my Courage more agree.</l>
                     <l>Were but <hi>Irena</hi> safe, I'de go, and kill</l>
                     <l>These Bassa's, and my own revenge fulfill.</l>
                     <l>But since she is unsafe; Those thoughts as yet</l>
                     <l>Do more of Valour, then of Love admit.</l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:49923:37"/>
                     <l>I'le once again go to her, and I'le trie,</l>
                     <l>If yet <hi>Irena</hi> will consent to flie.</l>
                     <l>Which if she does, I then in a short time</l>
                     <l>Will gather force, to punish their bold crime.</l>
                     <l>But if from flying she does still refrain,</l>
                     <l>I'le try what by my presence I can gain</l>
                     <l>Upon the Souldiers. For perhaps I may</l>
                     <l>Make 'em lay down their Arms, and yet obey,</l>
                     <l>But if this fails, with those few Guards I have</l>
                     <l>I'le strive, <hi>Irena</hi> and my self to save.</l>
                     <l>In her defence I'le die, or I'le prevent</l>
                     <l>These villains of their black and base intent.</l>
                     <l>'Twill be a comfort, if Fate grants that I</l>
                     <l>In her defence, may yet have leave to die:</l>
                     <l>And in my death I shall far happier prove</l>
                     <l>Then ever I have yet been in my Love.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49923:37"/>
                  <head>Actus IV. Scena VI.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the</hi> Aga <hi>in a disguise.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>So, I am now at last escap'd from the Bassa's</l>
                     <l>(Who will now quickly assault the Palace),</l>
                     <l>And am come here to act my own revenge.</l>
                     <l>This disguise has as yet preserv'd me from</l>
                     <l>Discov'ry, 'twas well I enter'd in</l>
                     <l>The Palace by a private way, Or else</l>
                     <l>Perhaps I had run some danger. I find</l>
                     <l>Some alteration here, some of those Guards</l>
                     <l>I trusted most, and that guarded <hi>Irena</hi>'s</l>
                     <l>Lodgings, I find displac'd, And other of</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mustapha</hi>'s Souldiers admitted i' their rooms.</l>
                     <l>And though we've force to execute our resolution,</l>
                     <l>Yet I fear that either the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s presence,</l>
                     <l>Or his promises, may make 'em (how resolute</l>
                     <l>Soever now they seem) to lay down their</l>
                     <l>Arms: Should this happen (which my own guilt makes</l>
                     <l>Me to suspect) then I am lost; Have not</l>
                     <l>I heard the <hi>Sultan</hi> to resolve my death?</l>
                     <l>And were not I a fool, that having means</l>
                     <l>Now to preserve my self, and be reveng'd</l>
                     <l>If I should be accessary to my own ruine?</l>
                     <l>No; now is the time of my revenge,</l>
                     <l>And I'le not defer it.</l>
                     <l>I have here hard-by, four or five Persons</l>
                     <l>(In whom I dare confide) disguis'd like my self:</l>
                     <l>Assisted by these, I'le watch an opportunitie,</l>
                     <l>And go and kill the <hi>Sultan.</hi> And then I'le</l>
                     <l>Give out, he perish'd i'th' assault.</l>
                     <l>He being dead, my fears will too die with him;</l>
                     <l>And with young <hi>Bajazet</hi> (before that I</l>
                     <l>Lay down my Arms) I'le make my own conditions.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan,</hi> your Fate is now resolv'd; 'tis I</l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:49923:38"/>
                     <l>That am the Ruler of your destiny.</l>
                     <l>Your ruine now so firmly is decreed</l>
                     <l>Fate cannot alter, but it must succeed.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. V. SCEN: I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet <hi>in the Palace Garden.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>THese villains still in treacherie combine,</l>
                     <l>And now resolve to act what they design</l>
                     <l>The time draws neer, The day has run its race</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Cynthia</hi> now supplies her Brother's place.</l>
                     <l>Their crime's so Monstrous, that they fear the light,</l>
                     <l>And dare not act their Treason but by night.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi>'s generous too, and seems to run</l>
                     <l>To meet those dangers, I wou'd have her shun.</l>
                     <l>But I have given to <hi>Mustapha</hi> command;</l>
                     <l>Their pow'r and their furie to withstand,</l>
                     <l>Whil'st by my presence, I strive to prevent</l>
                     <l>Their horrid Crime, and frustrate their intent —</l>
                     <l>Ha! What noise is that I hear —</l>
                     <stage>Hears a noise.</stage>
                     <l>Methinks I perceive some Persons coming</l>
                     <l>Towards me.</l>
                     <l>The Moon's pale beams affords me light enough</l>
                     <l>To discover they are Women.</l>
                     <l>And if I'm not deceiv'd, 'tis <hi>Irena,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Perinthia,</hi> 'Tis so —</l>
                     <l>What makes she now here at this time of night?</l>
                     <l>Just now I left her in her Chamber,</l>
                     <l>It cannot sure be fear that drives her forth,</l>
                     <l>She was then so resolute.</l>
                     <l>What should be the cause on't I can't imagine;</l>
                     <l>But I'le conceal my self, whats'ere it be</l>
                     <stage>Conceals himself.</stage>
                     <l>Till that the Cause either I hear or see.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:49923:38"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Irena <hi>and</hi> Perinthia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>But for the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Coming to me,</l>
                     <l>We had bin here before.</l>
                     <l>The time is now expir'd, And yet I see</l>
                     <l>None here; sure somthing is fallen out</l>
                     <l>Unexpected, that makes 'em stay so long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Persons when they're imploy'd about</l>
                     <l>Occasions of this Nature, cannot keep</l>
                     <l>Their promise to a minute,</l>
                     <l>But I dare engage, it will not be long</l>
                     <l>Ere they come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>In the mean while,</l>
                     <l>Let's retire into that Arbour,</l>
                     <l>And sing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Well agreed.</l>
                     <stage>They retire into an Arbour, and sing.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Song.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Though to our Sex 'tis that Love owes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'What of his pow'r the world yet knowes;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And 'tis our eyes that does inspire</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mens hearts with Love, and with desire:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Wer't not for us, the world would be</hi>
                        </l>
                        <stage>Enter <hi>Just.</hi> and <hi>Hon</hi> They listen to the Song.</stage>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Both from Lov's pow'r and Empire free.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet Love still with his golden Darts</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ne're spares to wound our tender hearts.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>We're rob'd by that ungrateful Boy,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Both of our Freedome, and our Joy.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He ne're considers 'tis our Eyes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That gains him such a glorious Prize.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then let's not Lovers make dispair,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But be as kind, as we are fair;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Since from Love's Empire, nor his pow'r</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>We cannot free our selves an hou'r.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Beautie's a shield too weak to prove</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Defence, against the Darts of Love,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:49923:39"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>This Musick far excels that o'the Sphears,</l>
                     <l>Methinks I'm ravish'd with Coelestial harmony.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Where two Coelestial voyces so combine,</l>
                     <l>The Musick cannot chuse, but be Divine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, Let's go to 'em.
<stage>Ire. <hi>and</hi> Per. <hi>come out of the Arbour</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>But see, they're here.</l>
                     <l>Madam, I hope we've not made you stay here</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Irena.</stage>
                     <l>Long; If we have, we humbly beg your pardon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <stage>Aside.</stage>
                     <l>Ha! Who are these, I grow suspitious;</l>
                     <l>But I'le conceal my self, till that I make</l>
                     <l>Further discovery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>There needs no pardon, where there's no offence.</l>
                     <l>I attributed your stay to your occasions,</l>
                     <l>Not to your neglect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Occasions did indeed take us up</l>
                     <l>More time then we imagin'd, else we had</l>
                     <l>Waited on you sooner.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>The time's not long expir'd,</l>
                     <l>You've bin prettie punctual.</l>
                     <l>What, are all things now in readiness?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, they are; Our Friends only expects</l>
                     <l>Our return for to assault the Palace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! What is't I hear — Assault the Palace— <stage>Aside.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are these in League too with the Bassa's?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>But what need you put it to the hazard</l>
                     <l>Of an Assault, and tempt your Fate, Can't you</l>
                     <l>Convey us out, by the way you enter in?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>No Madam, that's impossible—</l>
                     <l>The Garden is (as you know) moated round</l>
                     <l>And has but one door, which is strongly guarded.</l>
                     <l>We are forc'd to slide o're the Moat by a rope,</l>
                     <l>Which from this side the Eunuch throws us,</l>
                     <l>And which we fasten to the other side</l>
                     <l>O'the Moat, and then climb o're the Wall</l>
                     <l>By a Ladder of ropes.</l>
                     <l>Our intent is first to fall upon those Guards</l>
                     <l>That keep the Garden door, and so to force</l>
                     <l>Our passage through the Garden to your lodgings.</l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:49923:39"/>
                     <l>The disorder, and confusion things are now in</l>
                     <l>Will much facilate our design.</l>
                     <l>The Bassa's, and Souldiers, incens'd to see</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> to adore you, are now</l>
                     <l>Upon the point to assault the Palace.</l>
                     <l>And these villains, these Barbarians,</l>
                     <l>Dares be so impious as to threaten</l>
                     <l>Your destruction, which we by our speedy</l>
                     <l>Assault hope to prevent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> told me of the Bassa's intentions,</l>
                     <l>And would have had me either have fled,</l>
                     <l>Or conceal'd my self to avoid their furie;</l>
                     <l>But I refus'd it, knowing that then I</l>
                     <l>Should have disappointed you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>Heav'n, what is't I hear? was it to go</l>
                        <l>Along with these villains, that she refus'd it?</l>
                        <l>Was it for these she slighted my affection?</l>
                        <l>I can contain no longer, I must go to 'em.</l>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Discovers himself, and goes to 'em</hi> Irena <hi>spies the</hi> Sultan</stage>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan!</hi> O Heav'n we are undone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah cruel Fate, nothing but this accident</l>
                     <l>Could make us miserable.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <l>Whos'ere you are that intrude thus boldly</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Iust. <hi>and</hi> Hon. <hi>pointing to</hi> Ire.</stage>
                     <l>Into this Ladies company, your Lives</l>
                     <l>Shall pay the forfeit of your presumption:</l>
                     <l>Speak, Who are you? What's your names?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>My name (proud <hi>Sultan</hi>) I was ne're asham'd</l>
                     <l>To own; 'Tis <hi>Justinianus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>And mine <hi>Honorius.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <stage>Aside.</stage>
                        <l>Heav'n, What's my offence,</l>
                        <l>That you raise up my dead enemies</l>
                        <l>(Together with my Subjects) to conspire</l>
                        <l>My ruine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <l>Were not you slain?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>No, you see we are alive,</l>
                     <l>And alive to dispute these Ladies with you.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi>'s mine, and so long as I have life,</l>
                     <stage>Layes his hand upon his sword.</stage>
                     <l>And can rule this, she must ne're be yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Audacious villain, <hi>Irena</hi> must be mine,</l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49923:40"/>
                     <l>For she shall ne're be yours.</l>
                     <l>I'le make you quit your bold pretensions</l>
                     <l>Together with your Life.</l>
                     <l>Ho Guards! Who's there?—
<stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Aga <hi>disguis'd, with</hi> 4 <hi>or</hi> 5 <hi>more.</hi> Just. <hi>and</hi> Hon. <hi>draw. Discovers himself.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here, kill these slaves —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis you that first must die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! betray'd—</l>
                     <l>Villains, dare you attempt my Life?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, you resolv'd my death!</l>
                     <l>I over-heard your Discourse;</l>
                     <l>But I'le prevent your Design —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Ho <hi>Mustapha</hi> —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, ne're call, he's other-ways imploy'd,</l>
                     <l>There's none neer to assist you, You must die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le sell my life then dearly—</l>
                     <stage>Draws and fights.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, let's not stand idle, and be Spectators</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Hon.</stage>
                     <l>Of this unequal Combat—</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sultan,</hi> you shall find those lives</l>
                     <l>You would have took from us,</l>
                     <l>We'll now imploy to defend yours.</l>
                     <l>See this victim, I offer to your revenge —</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Kills the</hi> Aga. Maho <hi>and</hi> Hon. <hi>kill two of the others, the rest fly.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Generous men pardon the first transports</l>
                     <l>Of my passion, You've preserv'd a Life</l>
                     <l>Shall be at your devotion, and you've oblig'd</l>
                     <l>A Prince, that will not be ungrateful.</l>
                     <l>I know not how to recompence the generosity you've shown;</l>
                     <l>But I'le studie to find out a reward,</l>
                     <l>Equall to your deserts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Prince, what we've done, we were oblig'd</l>
                     <l>By Honour to perform; But if you think</l>
                     <l>It merits an acknowledgment, Grant us,</l>
                     <l>As a reward, the disposal of these Ladies;</l>
                     <l>And let me carry the fair <hi>Irena</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where I think fit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! Ask what you will besides,</l>
                     <l>And I will grant it, Ask half my Empire,</l>
                     <l>And you shall have it freely. But to part</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Irena,</hi> alas, it lies not in my pow'r;</l>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49923:40"/>
                     <l>I cannot grant it— Pray ask somthing else.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>All else I scorn —</l>
                     <l>Know that <hi>Irena</hi>'s mine, by her Father's,</l>
                     <l>Her Prince's, and her own Election.</l>
                     <l>Know, I have pow'r besides to force that from you,</l>
                     <l>Which now I ask.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I know your pow'r, and scorn it:</l>
                     <l>Were I not oblig'd by gratitude, your threats</l>
                     <l>Should not force <hi>Irena</hi> from me.</l>
                     <l>Madam, is't true that you affect <hi>Justinianus?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Irena.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I were unjust, an if I should deny it:</l>
                     <l>I so affect him, that 'tis impossible</l>
                     <l>I should ere affect an other.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble <hi>Justinianus,</hi> give me but leave</l>
                     <l>To trie, if I can dispose my heart to shake off</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi>'s Fetters, and forget her Charm's!</l>
                     <l>And I'le endeavour to yield to your desires.</l>
                     <stage>Just. <hi>bows and retires with the rest to a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Stage and whispers.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>What a strange and cruel Law</l>
                     <l>Does my hard Destiny impose upon me</l>
                     <l>Either I must forsake <hi>Irena,</hi> or be</l>
                     <l>Ungrateful to the Preserver of my Life.</l>
                     <l>To forsake <hi>Irena</hi> (Ah, cruel Fate!)</l>
                     <l>'Tis a Task my heart cannot yet submit to.</l>
                     <l>Yet when I consider how gen'rously</l>
                     <l>He expos'd to danger that Life</l>
                     <l>I wou'd have took from him, to defend mine:</l>
                     <l>And how he reveng'd me on the Perfidious</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aga,</hi> I must confess I owe him</l>
                     <l>No common effects of Gratitude.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi> loves my Rival, and by her own</l>
                     <l>Confession, can ne're affect an other:</l>
                     <l>And I could ne're yet gain the least int'rest</l>
                     <l>In her heart. 'Tis wisdome, and discretion</l>
                     <l>To quit that gen'rously, which we can't preserve.</l>
                     <l>Should I deny him he has pow'r to force</l>
                     <l>Her from me, and I no pow'r to defend her.</l>
                     <l>The Bassa's will now quickly assault the Palace;</l>
                     <l>And they on the other side threaten her</l>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49923:41"/>
                     <l>Destruction; And I had rather see her in</l>
                     <l>A gen'rous Rival's Arms, then see her expos'd</l>
                     <l>To the fury of those Slaves.</l>
                     <l>I'le strive to subdue my Passion,</l>
                     <l>And bestow her on his merits.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Justinianus</hi> was gen'rous, and sav'd my Life,</l>
                     <l>And I'le be gen'rous, and bestow <hi>Irena</hi> on him.</l>
                     <l>'Tis his gen'rosity has vanquish'd me:</l>
                     <l>Thus to be conquer'd is no shame, I yield;</l>
                     <l>But 'tis to gratitude I quit the field.</l>
                     <stage>Goes to 'em.</stage>
                     <l>Madam, 'tis no easie matter</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Irena.</stage>
                     <l>For a Person captivated by your fair Eyes</l>
                     <l>To regain his Liberty, and yield up his</l>
                     <l>Pretensions to his Rival! 'Tis a task</l>
                     <l>Too hard for frail Humanitie:</l>
                     <l>But the Obligations I have to <hi>Justinianus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are so great, that they cannot be cancell'd</l>
                     <l>But by a generositie as great as his.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Takes</hi> Irena <hi>by the band and presents her to</hi> Just.</stage>
                     <l>Here, <hi>Justinianus,</hi> receive from me</l>
                     <l>The fair <hi>Irena;</hi> you sav'd my Life,</l>
                     <l>And I bestow upon you the thing</l>
                     <l>I most esteem.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a gift (Great <hi>Sultan</hi>) I more esteem,</l>
                     <l>Then if you had bestow'd your Throne upon me.</l>
                     <l>I want words to thank you, but my actions</l>
                     <l>Shall express my gratitude.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Gen'rous Prince, you've oblig'd a Lady, that</l>
                     <l>Though she could never yet affect your Person,</l>
                     <l>Yet she now adores your Vertue.</l>
                     <l>You've obtain'd more glory by thus conquering</l>
                     <l>Of your self, then 'ere you did by triumphing</l>
                     <l>O're your enemies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Was it because my Rival you did Love,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Irena.</stage>
                     <l>That I your heart to Love, could never move.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>My Love long since was to his merits due,</l>
                     <l>But I retain Respect great Prince for you:</l>
                     <l>For by your gen'rous actions now I find</l>
                     <l>That Honour has a place within your mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:49923:41"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mustapha.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! Who are these?</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Aga</hi> kill'd—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes <hi>Mustapha,</hi> Heav'n</l>
                     <l>Has reveng'd me on that Traytor</l>
                     <l>By the hand of that valiant Person.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Pointing to</hi> Just.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Make haste, Great Sir, by your presence to allay</l>
                     <l>The Souldier's fury, or all will soon be lost.</l>
                     <l>The Bassa's has assaulted the Palace,</l>
                     <l>The Guards gave 'em free access, and those that</l>
                     <l>Defend <hi>Irena</hi>'s Lodgings, will be too weak</l>
                     <l>To make any long resistance, unless</l>
                     <l>The others fury be speedily prevented.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Go, <hi>Mustapha,</hi> incourage 'em</l>
                     <l>To hold out till I come to 'em:</l>
                     <l>Tell 'em, I'le be with 'em strait.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Must.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Prince, Let not this</l>
                     <l>Their treacherie alarm you.</l>
                     <l>Those Forces we thought to have imploy'd</l>
                     <l>Against you, shall now be imploy'd to serve you.</l>
                     <l>I have here hard-by five hundred valiant</l>
                     <l>And able Souldiers; Most of 'em has bin formerly</l>
                     <l>Officers under me; They are all in readiness,</l>
                     <l>And only wait my return. With these</l>
                     <l>I doubt not but to stop the Bassa's furie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Brave <hi>Justinianus,</hi> you lay</l>
                     <l>So many Obligations on me, that</l>
                     <l>I shall ne're be able to requite you;</l>
                     <l>I accept your gen'rous offer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Command the Garden-door</l>
                     <l>For to be open'd, that through the Garden</l>
                     <l>We may enter in the Palace!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Here take this Ring, and this:</l>
                     <stage>Gives him a Ring, and a Table-book, in which he first writes.</stage>
                     <l>These will procure you entrance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>But what shall we do to secure</l>
                     <l>These Ladies?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:49923:42"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Take you no care for that,</l>
                     <l>I'le engage my life to secure 'em</l>
                     <l>Till your return. But pray make haste.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>We'll make all haste imaginable.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Just. <hi>and</hi> Hon.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mustapha <hi>hastily.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>For Heav'ns sake Great Sir, make haste,</l>
                     <l>And save your self, for all's lost.</l>
                     <l>The Bassa's, and Souldiers assaulted us</l>
                     <l>With such fury, that we were forc'd to yield.</l>
                     <l>They now seek up and down the Palace for</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena,</hi> And vow that 'tis only her blood</l>
                     <l>That must appease their furie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Curs'd villains—</l>
                     <stage>Aside.</stage>
                     <l>Heav'n! How shall I keep my promise,</l>
                     <stage>Stamps.</stage>
                     <l>And preserve <hi>Irena; Justinianus</hi> cannot</l>
                     <l>Yet return—stay, Is there no way yet left</l>
                     <l>To preserve <hi>Irena,</hi> and my Empire;</l>
                     <l>Let me consider—Ha!</l>
                     <stage>Studies.</stage>
                     <l>'Twill do, They scarce e're saw her, and may</l>
                     <l>Be easily deceiv'd—</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mustapha,</hi> heark ye—</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Whispers</hi> Must.</stage>
                     <l>Make haste, and do as I command.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Commands shall be</l>
                     <l>With diligence perform'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit.</hi> Must.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, since your safety, and my promise</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Irena.</stage>
                     <l>Does require it: Be pleas'd that I may conceal you</l>
                     <l>(Till <hi>Justinianus</hi>'s return) in a Vault</l>
                     <l>Here in this Garden, a place so secret,</l>
                     <l>That 'tis not known to any, but my self.</l>
                     <l>Whil'st by my project I appease their strife,</l>
                     <l>And save at once my Empire, and your Life,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:49923:42"/>
                  <head>Act. V. Scen. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Zoganus, Carazias, Caly-bassa, Mahometes, <hi>and</hi> Souldiers <hi>with their Swords drawn.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>Where's this Sorceress, this Syren,</l>
                     <l>That thus inchants the <hi>Sultan?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, Where's the <hi>Sultan</hi> too?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>And the <hi>Aga,</hi> Where's he?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahometes.</speaker>
                     <l>They're all vanish'd sure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>I begin for to suspect the <hi>Aga,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We have not seen him since we began th' Assault</l>
                     <l>I fear he takes the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>An if he does,</l>
                     <l>He shall not scape our vengeance—</l>
                     <l>But come, Let's not delay, but seek 'em,</l>
                     <l>Lest they escape us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet <hi>and</hi> Mustapha.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Have you done, as I commanded?</l>
                     <l>Are things in readiness?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>Your commands Great <hi>Sultan,</hi> I've obey'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Come then, and follow me;</l>
                     <l>And be sure you make fast all the doors</l>
                     <l>That none come neer us,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Excunt.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Carazias, Zoganus, Caly-Bassa, Mahometes; <hi>and</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers <hi>with their Swords drawn, as before, below. And enter above in a Belcony, The</hi> Sultan <hi>with a Slave attir'd like</hi> Irena, <hi>and vail'd</hi> Mustapha. <hi>The Body of</hi> Aga, <hi>is brought upon the Belcony.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis strange that they should all escape us,</l>
                     <l>And that we can find none.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>This <hi>Irena</hi> sure's a Witch,</l>
                     <l>And has cast some Mist before our eyes.</l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:49923:43"/>
                     <l>Else we've search'd so diligently for 'em,</l>
                     <l>'T 'was impossible they should escape us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahometes.</speaker>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan, Irena,</hi> the <hi>Aga</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Mustapha,</hi> all fled, I wonder that we</l>
                     <l>Should meet with none!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>See here perfidious villains, the Persons</l>
                     <stage>From above.</stage>
                     <l>That you seek.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They look up amaz'd, and espie the</hi> Sultan, <hi>and the rest.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>The Sultan!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zoga.</speaker>
                     <l>And <hi>Irena!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahometes</speaker>
                     <l>There's <hi>Mustapha,</hi> and the <hi>Aga</hi> too!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! The <hi>Aga's</hi> dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahomet.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, villains; he has receiv'd the reward</l>
                     <l>Due to his Treachery;</l>
                     <l>'Tis what you must expect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahometes.</speaker>
                     <l>How came he dead?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>To his companions</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, let's not dispute that,</l>
                     <l>But let's revenge his Death:</l>
                     <l>Let's break open the doors, and kill</l>
                     <stage>Offers to force the doors.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi> in the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Arms.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahomet.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold Traytors —</l>
                     <l>See here, insolent slaves, cannot I affect</l>
                     <stage>Turns up her vail.</stage>
                     <l>This fair Creature, this Master-piece of Nature:</l>
                     <l>But must you murmure, turn Rebells, and threaten</l>
                     <l>Her destruction?</l>
                     <l>Who made you the Judges of my actions?</l>
                     <l>What villain is there amongst you all,</l>
                     <l>That, had he so Divine a Creature in his possession,</l>
                     <l>But would be unwilling to part with her?</l>
                     <l>Speak, in the word of a Prince, I give you</l>
                     <l>Libertie, freely to express your thoughts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>She's fair beyond imagination,</l>
                     <stage>Aside to his companions.</stage>
                     <l>I cannot blame him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor I, for affecting so Divine a Creature.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahometes.</speaker>
                     <l>I never thought <hi>Irena</hi> half so fair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>She surpasses all that I ever saw.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I see you are amaz'd, your silence,</l>
                     <l>And your whispers, declare you are asham'd</l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:49923:43"/>
                     <l>Of your Rebellion, And that you rather</l>
                     <l>Approve, then condemn my actions.</l>
                     <l>But I'le make you know, base slaves,</l>
                     <l>That you've bin deceiv'd in me.</l>
                     <l>Ambition (that Imperious Mistris of</l>
                     <stage>Pointing to his breast.</stage>
                     <l>Heroick Souls) reigns only here, And she</l>
                     <l>Will not admit a Rivall in my heart.</l>
                     <l>That I can conquer my other Passions,</l>
                     <l>Let this perswade ye—</l>
                     <stage>Stab's the slave.</stage>
                     <l>Nay, been't amaz'd at what I have perform'd;</l>
                     <l>'Tis you that forc'd me to this cruel action.</l>
                     <l>Let this example strike a terrour in you,</l>
                     <l>And think, that he that could thus sacrifice</l>
                     <l>The Person he ador'd, Because you thought her</l>
                     <l>An obstacle to his glory; Will not stick</l>
                     <l>To be reveng'd on his perfidious Subjects.</l>
                     <l>Think but what Oblations, I ought to offer</l>
                     <l>To appease the Ghost of this unfortunate fair-One,</l>
                     <l>And to expiate the Crime you've forc'd me</l>
                     <l>To commit. 'Tis only your speedy laying down your Arms,</l>
                     <l>And returning to your obedience can obtain</l>
                     <l>Pardon for your offence.</l>
                     <l>Such an action may appease the Furie</l>
                     <l>Of your incens'd Prince, and discharge you</l>
                     <l>From the infamy, which your black Rebellion</l>
                     <l>Has contracted on you;</l>
                     <l>Yet think not that this Action, nor this Language</l>
                     <l>Proceeds from fear, know I have pow'r</l>
                     <l>(If you persist still in your treacherie)</l>
                     <l>To force Obedience from you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! What noise is that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A shout within.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahomet,</speaker>
                     <l>Surely, <hi>Justinianus</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are now come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis not unlikely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49923:44"/>
                  <stage>Enter a Souldier.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                     <l>Make haste to succour us, or we are lost:</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To the</hi> Bassa's.</stage>
                     <l>We are assaulted so furiously (by enemies</l>
                     <l>Whom we know not) that we are forc'd to give</l>
                     <l>Ground. They crie, Long live the <hi>Sultan Mahomet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And assault us like so many Devils;</l>
                     <l>Nor can our number ought prevail against 'em.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahometes.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, go; we'll be with you strait:</l>
                     <stage>Exit Sold.</stage>
                     <l>This report agrees with the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s last words.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot imagine from whence this aid</l>
                     <l>Should come, unless it comes from Heav'n.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>I fear, Heav'n will punish us for our</l>
                     <l>Treacherie, Let's implore the <hi>Sultans</hi> mercie,</l>
                     <l>And return to our Obedience.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> himself has kill'd <hi>Irena,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who was the cause of our Rebellion;</l>
                     <l>And as the cause, so the Effects should cease.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Their faces denotes that they're troubled,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Must.</stage>
                     <l>And I hope a happy change.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>I do not doubt, but they'll return again</l>
                     <l>To their Obedience.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>The sooner we submit, the easier</l>
                     <stage>To his companions.</stage>
                     <l>We shall obtain our pardon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>Let's not then defer it—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carazias,</speaker>
                     <l>do you speak for us: you us'd</l>
                     <l>To have some int'rest with the <hi>Sultan.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, since you will have it so, I will—</l>
                     <l>That we've offended you (Dread Soveraign)</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Mahomet.</stage>
                     <l>Our Actions has but too clearly manifested,</l>
                     <l>And we acknowledg that we have deserv'd</l>
                     <l>The greatest punishments that the rage</l>
                     <l>Of our justly displeas'd Prince</l>
                     <l>Could inflict upon us.</l>
                     <l>Our crim's so horrid, that we almost despair</l>
                     <l>Of Pardon; And we've no other way</l>
                     <l>Left to obtain it, then by prostrating</l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49923:44"/>
                     <l>Our selves at your Royal feet, and imploring</l>
                     <stage>They kneel.</stage>
                     <l>Of your mercy. Think how much more noble 'tis</l>
                     <l>For a Prince to save, then to destroy his Subjects.</l>
                     <l>Such an Act of Clemency will oblige us</l>
                     <l>For the future, never to be disloyal.</l>
                     <l>That our Repentance is not feign'd, but real,</l>
                     <l>Lead us but forth against our Enemies,</l>
                     <l>And our Actions shall confirm it:</l>
                     <l>And we will endeavour by their blood</l>
                     <l>To wash off the stain that's now upon us—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahomet.</speaker>
                     <l>Rise, for this once I pardon you:</l>
                     <stage>They rise.</stage>
                     <l>But if e're you prove again disloyal,</l>
                     <l>Ne're hope for pardon.</l>
                     <l>You would have Wars, And I'le lead you forth</l>
                     <l>In dangers, where the stoutest of you</l>
                     <l>Shall be affraid to follow me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Prince, Lead us but forth,</l>
                     <l>And never doubt our courage, for we</l>
                     <l>Will either die, or conquer.</l>
                     <l>The Pardon you've granted us, has so oblig'd us,</l>
                     <l>That we confess, Great <hi>Mahomet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is as Gen'rous, as he's Just.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Justinianus, Honorius, <hi>and</hi> Souldiers, <hi>with their Swords drawn.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Who dares dispute it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To the</hi> Bassa's.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Zog.</speaker>
                     <l>Not we, we do confess it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>An if you did not,</l>
                     <l>I'd force you to confess it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure these are those</l>
                     <l>The Souldier spoke of.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aside.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Great <hi>Sultan!</hi> wherein</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To the</hi> Sultan.</stage>
                     <l>Can we now serve you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Brave Men, you've kept your word,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>From above to</hi> Just. <hi>and</hi> Hon.</stage>
                     <l>And I'm beholding to you both for my life,</l>
                     <l>And Empire, you need not now imploy your Valour</l>
                     <l>To reduce these Bassa's to Obedience.</l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:49923:45"/>
                     <l>They have promis'd me to return, and never more</l>
                     <l>To be disloyal; And on that promise</l>
                     <l>I've pardon'd 'em their past Transgression:</l>
                     <l>Stay but a little, and I'le come to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Sult. Must. <hi>carrying out the body of the Slave.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! What Ladie's that <hi>Mustapha</hi> carries out?</l>
                     <l>'Tis like <hi>Irena.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis like her; But 'tis not she,</l>
                     <l>But who's e're she's, she's either dead or wounded:</l>
                     <l>But here's the <hi>Sultan,</hi> he'l inform us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mahomet.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>What Lady's that Great Sir,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Bassa Mustapha</hi> carried away but now,</l>
                     <l>And that seems either dead, or wounded?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mahomet.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me but send these away,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Aside to</hi> Just. <hi>and</hi> Hon. <hi>To the</hi> Bassa's.</stage>
                     <l>And I'le inform you.</l>
                     <l>Go, and since you stir'd up the Souldiers to</l>
                     <l>Rebellion, reduce 'em again to obedience,</l>
                     <l>And settle all disorders.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Caraz.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Diligence</l>
                     <l>Shall manifest our Obedience.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Bassa's.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Now I'le tell you who that woman was:</l>
                     <l>You were no sooner gon, but word was brought me</l>
                     <l>That the Bassa's had forc'd the Guards to yield</l>
                     <l>And hunted up and down the Palace for <hi>Irena,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vowing, that if they found her, they would kill her.</l>
                     <l>Imagine how this perplext me; I knew</l>
                     <l>You could not return so soon, and I knew</l>
                     <l>Not how to keep the promise I had made you,</l>
                     <l>Nor long to conceal <hi>Irena</hi> from their furie.</l>
                     <l>At last I be thought me of this strategem.</l>
                     <l>Yesterday as I was looking out of a window</l>
                     <l>Of the Palace, I espide a most beauteous slave,</l>
                     <l>(And who methought resembled much <hi>Irena</hi>)</l>
                     <l>For a notorious crime she had committed</l>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49923:45"/>
                     <l>Drag'd along to Execution.</l>
                     <l>The resemblance which (in my fancie) she</l>
                     <l>Had with <hi>Irena,</hi> mov'd me to suspend</l>
                     <l>The Execution, and command her back to prison.</l>
                     <l>And as <hi>Irena</hi>'s danger then was great,</l>
                     <l>"The danger adding quickness to conceit,</l>
                     <l>I call'd to mind this slave.</l>
                     <l>And gave <hi>Mustapha</hi> command to disguise</l>
                     <l>Himself, and go and take the Key's of the</l>
                     <l>Prison from the Jaylor, and take from thence</l>
                     <l>The fair Slave, attire her like <hi>Irena,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And bring her to me. Thinking (as afterwards</l>
                     <l>It happen'd) that the Bassa's, who had seldome</l>
                     <l>(Or scarce ever) seen <hi>Irena,</hi> might be easily</l>
                     <l>Deceiv'd, and mistake the counterfeit, for</l>
                     <l>The true one; Hoping by this Slave's death,</l>
                     <l>(As you see 'tis happend) to appease their</l>
                     <l>Rebellion, And at once to save my Empire,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Irena</hi>'s Life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>But <hi>Irena,</hi> and <hi>Perinthia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where are they?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I was forc'd (to save 'em from the Souldiers</l>
                     <l>Furie) to conceal 'em in a Vault, in</l>
                     <l>The Garden. But I have sent <hi>Mustapha</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To fetch em hither, and he'll strait be here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, Lets go meet em.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>See, They're here.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:49923:46"/>
                  <head>Act. V. Scen. III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> to <hi>'em</hi> Mustapha, Irena, <hi>and</hi> Perinthia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Go to the Bassa's <hi>Mustapha,</hi> and see
<stage>To Must.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>If that their words do with effects agree.</l>
                     <l>See if their Arms they have, as yet laid down,</l>
                     <l>And if they've from disorders freed the Town.
<stage>
                           <hi>Exit.</hi> Must. <hi>To</hi> Irena.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, you're safe I see, and now I must</l>
                     <l>Confess, that Fortune is both kind, and just.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm safe 'tis true, But I'm perplext to know,</l>
                     <l>That 'tis an others ruine makes me so.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mustapha</hi> has related to me</l>
                     <l>The Slave's sad story —</l>
                     <l>I pitie her sad Fate, that she should be</l>
                     <l>So miserable, to have dy'd for me.</l>
                     <l>Would it had lay'n in my pow'r</l>
                     <l>To have sav'd her life —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>To recall what is past, is now too late:</l>
                     <l>I envie, not compassionate, her Fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I had no other way left to prevent</l>
                     <l>The Bassa's furie, or their dire intent.</l>
                     <l>She dy'd, the Empire, and your life to save;</l>
                     <l>She had a Fate too glorious for a Slave.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Her death was requisite to save th' Empire —</l>
                     <l>As things then stood, it was the only way</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sultan</hi> had, their furie to allay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>Wer't not for that, it wou'd yet grieve me more,</l>
                     <l>If she had only dy'd upon my score.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Though Madam, now all seems to be appeas'd</l>
                     <l>And that I hope their furie now is ceas'd.</l>
                     <l>And though I'le shortly settle things so well,</l>
                     <l>That for the future they shall ne're rebell:</l>
                     <l>Yet for the present, as things stand, I must</l>
                     <l>Not give 'em the least cause for to mistrust</l>
                     <l>The cheat I've put upon 'em, that would be</l>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49923:46"/>
                     <l>Abrave pretext to be reveng'd on me.</l>
                     <l>To prevent this, Madam I must desire</l>
                     <l>That you'd be pleas'd for some-time to retire</l>
                     <l>From Court, whil'st I so settle all things here</l>
                     <l>That without danger you may then appear:</l>
                     <l>And though your absence will afflict my breast,</l>
                     <l>Yet I am forc'd to make you this request.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>It is (Great Prince) as requisite, as due,</l>
                     <l>And 'tis the same I would have made to you.</l>
                     <l>I'le strait absent my self, without delay,</l>
                     <l>To prevent what might happen by my stay.</l>
                     <l>To your request, you see that I incline,</l>
                     <l>Be now as generous, and grant me mine.</l>
                     <l>And give me leave to go with <hi>Justinianus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Whither is it Madam you intend to go?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>To <hi>Italy</hi> Great Sir, tis his intent</l>
                     <l>To carry me, if you please to consent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>We'll there conceal our names, that we may be</l>
                     <l>Both from suspition, and discov'ry free.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>The Bassa's think me kill'd, and ne're shall know</l>
                     <l>To their delusion I my safety owe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, although't be hard, and that my heart</l>
                     <l>With you, so soon, can scarce consent to part.</l>
                     <l>Yet your request I grant, for though 't be still</l>
                     <l>Against my self, I must obey your will.</l>
                     <l>Your absence too may be a means to cure</l>
                     <l>Me of those torments, which I still indure.</l>
                     <l>For though by gratitude my Lov's supprest,</l>
                     <l>Yet there remains some sparks within my breast.</l>
                     <l>Love is a flame, when kindl'd by your Eyes,</l>
                     <l>That is more lasting, nor so soon it dyes;</l>
                     <l>Now I'm resolv'd to court the wars again,</l>
                     <l>And by diversion strive to cure my pain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>Since to <hi>Irena</hi> you have bin so free,</l>
                     <l>Be pleas'd Great Prince to grant the like to me;</l>
                     <l>And give me liberty to go with my <hi>Honorius.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm to him so oblig'd, Madam, I grant</l>
                     <l>What you request; But 'tis too small, I want</l>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:49923:47"/>
                     <l>Something that's sitter for his valiant deeds.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a reward my Service far exceeds.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>But fair <hi>Perinthia,</hi> is't not true, confess,</l>
                     <l>That brave <hi>Honorius</hi> does your Heart possess.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>His vertues (Generous <hi>Sultan</hi>) are so known,</l>
                     <l>I need not blush that Passion for to own:</l>
                     <l>Nor do I think it merits an excuse,</l>
                     <l>Since 'tis his Vertues does my Love produce.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Then Madam, give me leave for to bestow,</l>
                     <l>What both of us to his great Merits ow:</l>
                     <l>And let me have the Honour to unite,</l>
                     <l>What to devide, Fate long has took delight.</l>
                     <l>Receive Brave-Man what's to your merits due,
<stage>
                           <hi>To</hi> Hon.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis a reward by Heav'n design'd for you.</l>
                     <l>Receive from me her hand, and for her heart,
<stage>Presents her hand to him.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>You hear, already you enjoy that part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Majestick <hi>Sultan,</hi> you've bestow'd that on me,</l>
                     <l>Which obliges me for ever to you.</l>
                     <l>Honour and Vertue equally do rest,</l>
                     <l>And find a Lodging in your gen'rous breast.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mustapha.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>There's none (Great <hi>Sultan</hi>) dares your pow'r with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand,</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers now obey what you command.</l>
                     <l>The Bassa's keep their promise, and allow</l>
                     <l>Those very actions, they condemn'd but now:</l>
                     <l>The Town is quiet, no disorder more,</l>
                     <l>And things are now just as they were before.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm glad to hear, all is appeas'd so well,</l>
                     <l>But since 'twas Ease, that made 'em thus rebell,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Peloponesus</hi> I will strait invade,</l>
                     <l>And thence I'le lead 'em to besiege <hi>Belgrade.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But <hi>Mustapha,</hi> 'tis fitting you should be</l>
                     <l>Rewarded, for your so great Loyaltie:</l>
                     <l>The Visier's place is vacant, And 'tis due</l>
                     <l>That place should be supply'd by none but you:</l>
                     <l>Your merits do deserve it, And I here,</l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:49923:47"/>
                     <l>Of all my Empire, make you Grand-Visier.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Must.</speaker>
                     <l>What I have done, Duty oblig'd me to,</l>
                     <l>Th'reward's too great for me, But worthy you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Now <hi>Justinianus,</hi> Let me yet once more</l>
                     <l>Bestow that on you, which I did before.</l>
                     <l>It is a gift can't be too often giv'n:</l>
                     <l>Can we receive blessings too oft from Heav'n?</l>
                     <l>Here once more receive the fair <hi>Irena</hi>
                        <stage>
                           <hi>Presents</hi> Irena <hi>to him.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>From me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Just.</speaker>
                     <l>And once more (upon my knees) I thank you,</l>
                     <l>And must confess (Great Prince) as is most due,</l>
                     <l>That all my happiness I ow to You.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ire.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Irena</hi> too (Brave <hi>Sultan</hi>) must confess,</l>
                     <l>That 'tis to you, she owes her happiness.</l>
                     <l>In my esteem you alwayes had a part,</l>
                     <l>Now next your Rivall, you possess my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>Since I enjoy that happiness, I will</l>
                     <l>(Though not your Lover) be your Servant still:</l>
                     <l>And he that rules the world, shall yield to you</l>
                     <l>What's to your Vertue, and your Beautie due.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <l>May you still prosp'rous and successfull be,
<stage>
                           <hi>To</hi> Maho.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Because you've bin so gen'rous to me:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Vertues are so great, That busie Fame</l>
                     <l>Shall now relate no wonders, but your name.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
                     <l>I lose my Mistris, but Fate makes amends,</l>
                     <l>For what I lose in Love, I gain in friends.</l>
                     <l>Fate has bin cruell, but at last we may,</l>
                     <l>After a stormie, hope a glorious day.
<stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:49923:48"/>
            <head>The Epilogue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>THE Play now being ended, I am come,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sent by the Author, for to know his doome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ladies 'tis to your Censure He'll submit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And swears none else shall judge what he has writ.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He vow's that Priviledge is only due</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To your fair Sex; He writ it to please you.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet he'd not have you think, 'tis his intent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To gain your Favours by a Complement.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He swears he's guilty, and convicted stands,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till that his Pardon's sign'd by your fair hands.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You are his Judges, and if he be crost</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Once by your Votes, his hope for ever's lost.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And though he hopes that you will think it fit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To pardon him, since that he does submit;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet he still doubts, if he shall Pardon find,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till that he hears it by your Hands is sign'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49923:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>